<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Astrobiology AI Digest</title>
  <subtitle>Hourly AI-curated papers on Origins of Life</subtitle>
  <link href="https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://github.com/champagnealexandre/ooldigest"/>
  <updated>2025-12-30T17:41:18.417547+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/feed.xml</id>
  <author><name>AI Agent</name></author>

  <entry>
    <title>[60] [KEYWORDS-OOL] [bioRxiv Subject Collection: Evolutionary Biology] Characterization of Z-DNA dynamics across the tree of life</title>
    <link href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.64898/2025.12.30.697008v1?rss=1"/>
    <id>https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.64898/2025.12.30.697008v1?rss=1</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T17:28:22+00:00</updated>
    <summary>The paper explores Z-DNA dynamics across various life forms, highlighting its regulatory roles and evolutionary pressures, which is relevant to understanding nucleic acid behavior in the context of life&#x27;s origins.</summary>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;strong&gt;Category:&lt;/strong&gt; KEYWORDS-OOL&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Source:&lt;/strong&gt; bioRxiv Subject Collection: Evolutionary Biology&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Score:&lt;/strong&gt; 60/100&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;AI Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; The paper explores Z-DNA dynamics across various life forms, highlighting its regulatory roles and evolutionary pressures, which is relevant to understanding nucleic acid behavior in the context of life&amp;#x27;s origins.&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;hr/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        Z-DNA/Z-RNA is an alternative left-handed nucleic acid conformation with established and emerging roles in gene regulation, immunity, and genome instability. However, its occurrence dynamics and lineage specificity across the tree of life have not yet been fully characterized. Utilizing the recently developed and improved Z-DNA searching tool, ZSeeker, we analyzed 281,139 complete organismal genomes, including multiple Telomere-to-Telomere genome assemblies, and generated genome-wide Z-nucleic acid maps, examined their topography, and compared them to dinucleotide-preserving controls. Cellular genomes featured pervasive Z-DNA enrichment relative to expectation, with enrichments of ~1.5 and ~1.7-fold in Bacteria and Archaea and ~3-fold in Eukaryota. In contrast, Viruses exhibited large differences between lineages, with modest enrichment in several DNA viral groups and pronounced depletion across RNA clades, most notably Influenza A/B strains. We built a LASSO regression model trained on non-Influenza viruses (cross-validated R2 {approx} 0.73), which identified GC content, genome type, and host type as the leading predictors for Z-nucleic acid density, yet it significantly over-predicted Z-RNA density in Influenza A/B. More than 99% of assemblies exceeded the +2 SD threshold, and a &amp;quot;typical Influenza&amp;quot; genome was predicted at 2.76 bp/kb compared to ~0.016 bp/kb observed (a ~170-fold overestimation based on chance alone). Together, these results reveal domain- and lineage-specific regimes: cellular genomes are enriched for Z-DNA consistent with regulatory roles, whereas influenza viruses appear to have undergone strong, lineage-specific depletion of Z-RNA-forming sequences, likely reflecting evolutionary pressure tied to host sensing pathways.
        &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#x27;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.64898/2025.12.30.697008v1?rss=1&#x27;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.64898/2025.12.30.697008v1?rss=1&quot;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
        </content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title>[60] [KEYWORDS-ASTROBIOLOGY] [Astrobiology] The Evolution in Coma Molecular Composition of Comet C/2017 K2 (PanSTARRS) Across the H2O Sublimation Zone: ALMA Imaging of an H2O-Dominated Coma</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-evolution-in-coma-molecular-composition-of-comet-c-2017-k2-panstarrs-across-the-h2o-sublimation-zone-alma-imaging-of-an-h2o-dominated-coma.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-evolution-in-coma-molecular-composition-of-comet-c-2017-k2-panstarrs-across-the-h2o-sublimation-zone-alma-imaging-of-an-h2o-dominated-coma.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-29T19:34:52+00:00</updated>
    <summary>The paper examines the molecular composition of comet C/2017 K2&#x27;s coma, relevant to astrobiology and origins of life studies, with a focus on water and evolution.</summary>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;strong&gt;Category:&lt;/strong&gt; KEYWORDS-ASTROBIOLOGY&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Source:&lt;/strong&gt; Astrobiology&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Score:&lt;/strong&gt; 60/100&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;AI Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; The paper examines the molecular composition of comet C/2017 K2&amp;#x27;s coma, relevant to astrobiology and origins of life studies, with a focus on water and evolution.&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;hr/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        We report a survey of molecular emission from cometary volatiles using the Atacama Large Millimeter/Submillimeter Array (ALMA) toward comet C/2017 K2 (PanSTARRS) carried out on UT 2022 September 21, 22, and 23 at a heliocentric distance (rh) of 2.1 au. These measurements of HCN, CS, CO, CH3OH, and H2CO (along with continuum emission from dust) […] The post The Evolution in Coma Molecular Composition of Comet C/2017 K2 (PanSTARRS) Across the H2O Sublimation Zone: ALMA Imaging of an H2O-Dominated Coma appeared first on Astrobiology .
        &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05662&quot;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05662&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.05662&quot;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.05662&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-evolution-in-coma-molecular-composition-of-comet-c-2017-k2-panstarrs-across-the-h2o-sublimation-zone-alma-imaging-of-an-h2o-dominated-coma.html&quot;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
        </content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title>[60] [KEYWORDS-ASTROBIOLOGY] [Astrobiology] Designing Peptide Fossils That Model the Evolution of the Bacterial Ferredoxin Fold</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/designing-peptide-fossils-that-model-the-evolution-of-the-bacterial-ferredoxin-fold.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/designing-peptide-fossils-that-model-the-evolution-of-the-bacterial-ferredoxin-fold.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-29T18:35:40+00:00</updated>
    <summary>The paper focuses on the evolution of bacterial ferredoxin folds, a core topic in the origins of life, and includes a DOI link, earning a robust base relevance score and a keyword bonus for &#x27;evolution&#x27;.</summary>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;strong&gt;Category:&lt;/strong&gt; KEYWORDS-ASTROBIOLOGY&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Source:&lt;/strong&gt; Astrobiology&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Score:&lt;/strong&gt; 60/100&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;AI Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; The paper focuses on the evolution of bacterial ferredoxin folds, a core topic in the origins of life, and includes a DOI link, earning a robust base relevance score and a keyword bonus for &amp;#x27;evolution&amp;#x27;.&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;hr/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        Electron transfer coupled to redox chemistry is at the heart of metabolism. The proteins responsible for moving electrons (protein electron carriers) must have emerged at the origin of life. The small iron–sulfur-binding bacterial ferredoxins were likely among these first proteins. Embedded within the ferredoxin sequence and structure is a symmetry that points to an ancient […] The post Designing Peptide Fossils That Model the Evolution of the Bacterial Ferredoxin Fold appeared first on Astrobiology .
        &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1021/jacsau.5c00863&quot;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.1021/jacsau.5c00863&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC12648291/&quot;&gt;[PubMed/NCBI] https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC12648291/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/jacsau.5c00863&quot;&gt;[Full Paper] https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/jacsau.5c00863&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/designing-peptide-fossils-that-model-the-evolution-of-the-bacterial-ferredoxin-fold.html&quot;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
        </content>
  </entry>
</feed>