<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Astrobiology AI Digest - All</title>
  <subtitle>Hourly AI-curated papers on Origins of Life</subtitle>
  <link href="https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/all.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://github.com/champagnealexandre/ooldigest"/>
  <updated>2026-01-01T19:53:11.445390+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/all.xml</id>
  <author><name>AI Agent</name></author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.GT updates on arXiv.org ➤ Multilevel Fair Allocation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24105"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24105</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Proposes polynomial-time algorithms for fair resource allocation across hierarchical (tree-structured) agent systems with matroid-rank utilities, a computational social choice topic unrelated to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24105v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: We introduce the concept of multilevel fair allocation of resources with tree-structured hierarchical relations among agents. While at each level it is possible to consider the problem locally as an allocation of an agent to its children, the multilevel allocation can be seen as a trace capturing the fact that the process is iterated until the leaves of the tree. In principle, each intermediary node may have its own local allocation mechanism. The main challenge is then to design algorithms which can retain good fairness and efficiency properties. In this paper we propose two original algorithms under the assumption that leaves of the tree have matroid-rank utility functions and the utility of any internal node is the sum of the utilities of its children. The first one is a generic polynomial-time sequential algorithm that comes with theoretical guarantees in terms of efficiency and fairness. It operates in a top-down fashion -- as commonly observed in real-world applications -- and is compatible with various local algorithms. The second one extends the recently proposed General Yankee Swap to the multilevel setting. This extension comes with efficiency guarantees only, but we show that it preserves excellent fairness properties in practice.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24105&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24105&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.NE updates on arXiv.org ➤ Generalising E-prop to Deep Networks</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24506"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24506</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This arXiv note generalizes the E-prop online learning framework to arbitrarily deep recurrent neural networks, enabling credit assignment across time and depth without backpropagation through time.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24506v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: Recurrent networks are typically trained with backpropagation through time (BPTT). However, BPTT requires storing the history of all states in the network and then replaying them sequentially backwards in time. This computation appears extremely implausible for the brain to implement. Real Time Recurrent Learning (RTRL) proposes an mathematically equivalent alternative where gradient information is propagated forwards in time locally alongside the regular forward pass, however it has significantly greater computational complexity than BPTT which renders it impractical for large networks. E-prop proposes an approximation of RTRL which reduces its complexity to the level of BPTT while maintaining a purely online forward update which can be implemented by an eligibility trace at each synapse. However, works on RTRL and E-prop ubiquitously investigate learning in a single layer with recurrent dynamics. However, learning in the brain spans multiple layers and consists of both hierarchal dynamics in depth as well as time. In this mathematical note, we extend the E-prop framework to handle arbitrarily deep networks, deriving a novel recursion relationship across depth which extends the eligibility traces of E-prop to deeper layers. Our results thus demonstrate an online learning algorithm can perform accurate credit assignment across both time and depth simultaneously, allowing the training of deep recurrent networks without backpropagation through time.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24506&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24506&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org ➤ Non-stationary dynamics of interspike intervals in neuronal populations</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23922"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23922</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:02+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops a population-density/Fokker–Planck framework to compute non-stationary inter-spike interval distributions and their linear response in integrate-and-fire neuronal populations, with no direct relevance to origins-of-life research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.23922v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: We study the joint dynamics of membrane potential and time since the last spike in a population of integrate-and-fire neurons using a population density framework. This leads to a two-dimensional Fokker-Planck equation that captures the evolution of the full neuronal state, along with a one-dimensional hierarchy of equations for the moments of the inter-spike interval (ISI). The formalism allows us to characterize the time-dependent ISI distribution, even when the population is far from stationarity, such as under time-varying external input or during network oscillations. By performing a perturbative expansion around the stationary state, we also derive an analytic expression for the linear response of the ISI distribution to weak input modulations.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23922&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23922&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.NE updates on arXiv.org ➤ Evolutionary Discovery of Sequence Acceleration Methods for Slab Geometry Neutron Transport</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24559"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24559</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:03+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Genetic programming is used to evolve novel convergence-acceleration formulas for neutron transport solvers in slab geometry, improving numerical convergence over classical techniques but with no direct connection to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24559v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: We present a genetic programming approach to automatically discover convergence acceleration methods for discrete ordinates solutions of neutron transport problems in slab geometry. Classical acceleration methods such as Aitken&amp;#x27;s delta-squared and Wynn epsilon assume specific convergence patterns and do not generalize well to the broad set of transport problems encountered in practice. We evolved mathematical formulas specifically tailored to SN convergence characteristics in this work. The discovered accelerator, featuring second differences and cross-product terms, achieved over 75 percent success rate in improving convergence compared to raw sequences - almost double that observed for classical techniques for the problem set considered. This work demonstrates the potential for discovering novel numerical methods in computational physics via genetic programming and attempts to honor Prof. Ganapol&amp;#x27;s legacy of advancing experimental mathematics applied to neutron transport.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24559&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24559&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math.DS updates on arXiv.org ➤ Neural Field Equations with random data</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:04+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Mathematical analysis of neural field evolution equations with random inputs, establishing existence/uniqueness/measurability and providing a foundation for uncertainty quantification in spatially discretized neural-field models.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2505.16343v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: We study neural field equations, which are prototypical models of large-scale cortical activity, subject to random data. We view this spatially-extended, nonlocal evolution equation as a Cauchy problem on abstract Banach spaces, with randomness in the synaptic kernel, firing rate function, external stimuli, and initial conditions. We determine conditions on the random data that guarantee existence, uniqueness, and measurability of the solution in an appropriate Banach space, and examine the regularity of the solution in relation to the regularity of the inputs. We present results for linear and nonlinear neural fields, and for the two most common functional setups in the numerical analysis of this problem. In addition to the continuous problem, we analyse in abstract form neural fields that have been spatially discretised, setting the foundations for analysing uncertainty quantification (UQ) schemes.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.NE updates on arXiv.org ➤ Decoupling Constraint from Two Direction in Evolutionary Constrained Multi-objective Optimization</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23945"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23945</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:05+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a constrained multi-objective evolutionary optimization algorithm (DCF2D) for engineering/benchmark problems, with no direct connection to origins-of-life or astrobiology beyond the generic use of “evolutionary” terminology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.23945v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Real-world Constrained Multi-objective Optimization Problems (CMOPs) often contain multiple constraints, and understanding and utilizing the coupling between these constraints is crucial for solving CMOPs. However, existing Constrained Multi-objective Evolutionary Algorithms (CMOEAs) typically ignore these couplings and treat all constraints as a single aggregate, which lacks interpretability regarding the specific geometric roles of constraints. To address this limitation, we first analyze how different constraints interact and show that the final Constrained Pareto Front (CPF) depends not only on the Pareto fronts of individual constraints but also on the boundaries of infeasible regions. This insight implies that CMOPs with different coupling types must be solved from different search directions. Accordingly, we propose a novel algorithm named Decoupling Constraint from Two Directions (DCF2D). This method periodically detects constraint couplings and spawns an auxiliary population for each relevant constraint with an appropriate search direction. Extensive experiments on seven challenging CMOP benchmark suites and on a collection of real-world CMOPs demonstrate that DCF2D outperforms five state-of-the-art CMOEAs, including existing decoupling-based methods.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23945&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23945&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math.DS updates on arXiv.org ➤ Approximate Controllability of Linear Fractional Impulsive Evolution Equations in Hilbert Spaces</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15114"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15114</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A pure mathematics/control-theory paper deriving criteria for approximate controllability of fractional impulsive evolution equations in Hilbert spaces, with no direct connection to origins-of-life or astrobiology beyond potential abstract modeling relevance.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2406.15114v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: This paper investigates the approximate controllability of linear fractional impulsive evolution equations in Hilbert spaces. The system under consideration involves the Caputo fractional derivative of order $0&amp;lt;\alpha\leq 1$, a closed linear operator generating a strongly continuous semigroup, and instantaneous state jumps governed by bounded linear impulse operators. We first derive an explicit representation of the mild solution by combining fractional solution operators with impulsive operators. Using this representation, we characterize the approximate controllability of the system through a necessary and sufficient condition expressed in terms of the convergence of an associated family of impulsive resolvent operators. This resolvent condition extends the classical criterion for approximate controllability to the fractional impulsive setting. To illustrate the applicability of our theoretical results, a concrete example is provided. The analysis presented here bridges the gap between the well-established theory for integer-order impulsive systems and the more complex fractional case, highlighting the distinct challenges and solutions arising from the interplay of fractional dynamics and impulsive effects.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15114&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15114&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.NE updates on arXiv.org ➤ Projection-based Adversarial Attack using Physics-in-the-Loop Optimization for Monocular Depth Estimation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24792"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24792</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops a physics-in-the-loop projected-light adversarial attack against monocular depth estimation neural networks, demonstrating real-world depth misestimation vulnerabilities, but it has no direct relevance to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24792v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: Deep neural networks (DNNs) remain vulnerable to adversarial attacks that cause misclassification when specific perturbations are added to input images. This vulnerability also threatens the reliability of DNN-based monocular depth estimation (MDE) models, making robustness enhancement a critical need in practical applications. To validate the vulnerability of DNN-based MDE models, this study proposes a projection-based adversarial attack method that projects perturbation light onto a target object. The proposed method employs physics-in-the-loop (PITL) optimization -- evaluating candidate solutions in actual environments to account for device specifications and disturbances -- and utilizes a distributed covariance matrix adaptation evolution strategy. Experiments confirmed that the proposed method successfully created adversarial examples that lead to depth misestimations, resulting in parts of objects disappearing from the target scene.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24792&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24792&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org ➤ Dynamical Learning in Deep Asymmetric Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05041"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05041</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:08+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This arXiv paper develops a local, gradient-free learning mechanism in asymmetric recurrent neural networks via dynamically accessible stable fixed points, offering only indirect conceptual relevance to origins-of-life questions through general principles of self-organization and adaptive dynamics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2509.05041v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: We investigate recurrent neural networks with asymmetric interactions and demonstrate that the inclusion of self-couplings or sparse excitatory inter-module connections leads to the emergence of a densely connected manifold of dynamically accessible stable configurations. This representation manifold is exponentially large in system size and is reachable through simple local dynamics, despite constituting a subdominant subset of the global configuration space. We further show that learning can be implemented directly on this structure via a fully local, gradient-free mechanism that selectively stabilizes a single task-relevant network configuration. Unlike error-driven or contrastive learning schemes, this approach does not require explicit comparisons between network states obtained with and without output supervision. Instead, transient supervisory signals bias the dynamics toward the representation manifold, after which local plasticity consolidates the attained configuration, effectively shaping the latent representation space. Numerical evaluations on standard image classification benchmarks indicate performance comparable to that of multilayer perceptrons trained using backpropagation. More generally, these results suggest that the dynamical accessibility of fixed points and the stabilization of internal network dynamics constitute viable alternative principles for learning in recurrent systems, with conceptual links to statistical physics and potential implications for biologically motivated and neuromorphic computing architectures.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05041&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05041&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org ➤ Epigenetic Control and Reprogramming-Induced Potential Landscapes of Gene Regulatory Networks: A Quantitative Theoretical Approach</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:09+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a dynamical mean-field theory for gene regulatory networks that explicitly includes epigenetic modifications (DNA methylation/histone marks) to map stable and oscillatory expression states, offering broad theoretical context for biological regulation but limited direct relevance to prebiotic origins of life.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24427v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: We develop an extended Dynamical Mean Field Theory framework to analyze gene regulatory networks (GRNs) incorporating epigenetic modifications. Building on the Hopfield network model analogy to spin glass systems, our approach introduces dynamic terms representing DNA methylation and histone modification to capture their regulatory influence on gene expression. The resulting formulation reduces high-dimensional GRN dynamics to effective stochastic equations, enabling the characterization of both stable and oscillatory states in epigenetically regulated systems. This framework provides a tractable and quantitative method for linking gene regulatory dynamics with epigenetic control, offering new theoretical insights into developmental processes and cell fate decisions.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org ➤ Hierarchical Loop Stabilization in Periodically Driven Elastic Networks</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:10+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Proposes an adaptation rule for periodically driven elastic transport networks showing that resonant vs anti-resonant pulsatile forcing can selectively stabilize loopy vs loop-less hierarchical architectures, a result more relevant to biological vascular remodeling than to prebiotic origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2503.19681v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: Network remodeling, or adaptation, in the presence of periodically driven forcings has hereto remained largely unexplored, despite the fact that a broad class of biological transport networks, e.g. animal vasculature, depends on periodic driving (pulsatility of the heart) to maintain flow. Short-term pulsatile dynamics of compliant vessels affects the long-term structures of adapting networks; however, what the correct adaptation rule is for pulsatile flows still remains an open question. Here we propose a new adaptation rule for periodically driven complex elastic networks that accounts for the effect of short-term pulsatile dynamics on the remodeling signal at long time-scales. Using this rule to adapt hierarchical elastic networks with multiple levels of looping, we show that very different network architectures are possible at steady-state depending on the driving frequency of the pulsatile source and the geometric asymmetry of the paths between the externally driven nodes of the network. Specifically resonant frequencies are shown to prioritize the stabilization of fully looped structures or higher level loops proximal to the source, whereas anti-resonant frequencies predominantly stabilize loop-less structures or lower-level loops distal to the source. Thus, this model offers a mechanism that can explain the stabilization of phenotypically diverse loopy network architectures in response to source pulsatility under physiologically relevant conditions and in the absence of other known loop stabilization mechanisms, such as random fluctuations in the load or perfusion homogenization.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.NE updates on arXiv.org ➤ GRASP: GRouped Activation Shared Parameterization for Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning and Robust Inference of Transformers</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04296"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04296</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:11+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces a parameter-efficient fine-tuning method (GRASP/StochGRASP) for transformers to improve robustness under noisy hardware inference, with no direct relevance to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.04296v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) provides a scalable alternative to full-model adaptation by updating only a small subset of parameters in large pre-trained models. We introduce GRASP - GRouped Activation Shared Parameterization - a lightweight PEFT framework that partitions the D-dimensional token representations of selected layers into K &amp;lt;&amp;lt; D groups and learns a shared scaling and shifting vector for each group. This grouped modulation reduces the number of trainable parameters significantly while preserving the ability of the model to learn task-specific features. Building on this formulation, we further propose StochGRASP, which learns Gaussian distributions as perturbations to the pre-trained weights rather than deterministic values. This probabilistic parameterization along with a noise-aware loss function formulation enables modelling hardware-level variability in programmed weights and significantly improves robustness under non-ideal inference conditions-an important requirement for deployment on edge-based emerging AI hardware. Across GLUE (RoBERTa-base &amp;amp; RoBERTa-large) and E2E NLG (GPT-2 Medium), GRASP matches or exceeds the performance of established PEFT methods while achieving an order of magnitude reduction in trainable parameters compared to LoRA and BitFit. Under varying levels of noise, StochGRASP consistently outperforms deterministic variants, demonstrating its suitability for energy-efficient and noise-prone hardware platforms.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04296&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04296&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org ➤ A chaotic lattice field theory in two dimensions</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22972"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22972</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:12+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops a statistical-mechanics/field-theory reformulation of spatiotemporal chaos on lattices using periodic-orbit (zeta function) techniques, with no direct connection to prebiotic chemistry, biosignatures, or origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2503.22972v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: We describe spatiotemporally chaotic (or turbulent) field theories discretized over d-dimensional lattices in terms of sums over their multi-periodic orbits. `Chaos theory&amp;#x27; is here recast in the language of statistical mechanics, field theory, and solid state physics, with the traditional periodic orbits theory of low-dimensional, temporally chaotic dynamics a special, one-dimensional case. In the field-theoretical formulation, there is no time evolution. Instead, treating the temporal and spatial directions on equal footing, one determines the spatiotemporally periodic orbits that contribute to the partition sum of the theory, each a solution of the system&amp;#x27;s defining deterministic equations, with sums over time-periodic orbits of dynamical systems theory replaced here by sums of d-periodic orbits over d-dimensional spacetime geometries, the weight of each orbit given by the Jacobian of its spatiotemporal orbit Jacobian operator. The weights, evaluated by application of the Bloch theorem to the spectrum of periodic orbit&amp;#x27;s Jacobian operator, are multiplicative for spacetime orbit repeats, leading to a spatiotemporal zeta function formulation of the theory in terms of prime orbits.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22972&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22972&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org ➤ Experimental Study on Fracture Structure of Sumi-Wari</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24830"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24830</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:13+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Soft-matter physics study of surface-tension–driven fracture patterns in carbon-black sumi films on water–glycerol subphases, offering only indirect relevance to origins-of-life via general insights into interfacial mechanics and pattern formation in aqueous thin films.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24830v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Local variations in surface tension can induce complex fracture dynamics in thin interfacial films. Here, we investigate the fracture patterns that emerge when a localized surface-tension perturbation is applied to a sumi film supported on a water-glycerol subphase. Sumi is a traditional Japanese carbon black ink, and this process, referred to as sumi-wari, produces aesthetically pleasing, star-shaped crack patterns with multiple spikes radiating from the perturbation site. The number of crack spikes increases with the viscosity of the subphase, controlled here by the addition of glycerol. Atomic force microscopy measurements reveal that the effective stiffness of the sumi f ilm decreases as glycerol concentration increases. This suggests a strong coupling between the subphase properties and the mechanics of the sumi film. To capture the dynamics of sumi-wari, a phenomenological model is outlined, based on an overdamped equation of motion for particles connected by breakable springs. Numerical simulations reproduce both the morphology and the experimental trends of sumi-wari: the number of cracks and their temporal evolution depend on the spring stiffness, mirroring the behavior observed for subphases with different viscosities. These findings demonstrate how the interplay between surface-tension gradients, subphase properties, and film mechanics governs local fracture and pattern formation in fluid-supported thin films
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24830&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24830&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org ➤ Contact-Geometric Dynamics for Dissipative Nonlinear Systems</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04526"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04526</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops a contact-geometry and probabilistic framework for dissipative nonlinear wave dynamics (2D complex Ginzburg–Landau), yielding exact solutions and a phase-transition-like switching line for pattern formation, with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life via general self-organization theory.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.04526v3 Announce Type: replace Abstract: Dissipative nonlinear waves are ubiquitous in nonequilibrium physical systems, and the Complex Ginzburg-Landau Equation (CGLE) serves as a fundamental model for describing their dynamics. This paper develops a contact-geometric formulation of dissipative field theories, extending the least constraint theorem to complex fields and establishing a link between contact geometry and probability measures. By applying this framework to the 2D CGLE, we derive the dissipative Contact Hamilton-Jacobi (CHJ) equation, which governs the evolution of the action functional. Through canonical transformation and travelling-wave reduction, exact solutions of the CHJ equation are obtained. From a probabilistic perspective, we derive the probability density functional of the 2D CGLE, identify a universal switching line that separates different dynamical regimes, and reveal a first-order periodon--soliton phase transition with a hysteresis loop. The conserved contact potential is identified as the key geometric quantity governing pattern formation in dissipative media, playing a role analogous to energy in conservative systems. This contact-geometric framework provides a unified analytical tool for studying pattern selection and state transitions.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04526&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04526&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org ➤ Neural Field Equations with random data</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:15+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Mathematical analysis of neural field (cortical activity) equations with random inputs, establishing existence/uniqueness/measurability and discretization foundations for uncertainty quantification, with no substantive origins-of-life relevance.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2505.16343v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: We study neural field equations, which are prototypical models of large-scale cortical activity, subject to random data. We view this spatially-extended, nonlocal evolution equation as a Cauchy problem on abstract Banach spaces, with randomness in the synaptic kernel, firing rate function, external stimuli, and initial conditions. We determine conditions on the random data that guarantee existence, uniqueness, and measurability of the solution in an appropriate Banach space, and examine the regularity of the solution in relation to the regularity of the inputs. We present results for linear and nonlinear neural fields, and for the two most common functional setups in the numerical analysis of this problem. In addition to the continuous problem, we analyse in abstract form neural fields that have been spatially discretised, setting the foundations for analysing uncertainty quantification (UQ) schemes.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org ➤ Pair Space in Classical Mechanics III. Some Four-Body Central Configurations</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:16+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This mathematical-physics paper classifies certain four-body central configurations using a pair-space formalism, with no direct connection to origins-of-life chemistry, prebiotic processes, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.23730v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: We study central configurations in the four body problem, i.e., configurations in which the forces on all the bodies point to a fixed, single point in space. The newly formulated pair-space formalism yields a set of vectorial equations that fully characterize such configurations. We investigate a sub-class of solutions in which at least two pairs of inter-body distances are equal. The only such non-collinear configurations are the tetrahedron (the unique non-planar configuration), kites and the isosceles trapezium. The specific shapes (internal angles) are determined by the ratio of the masses of the bodies. Mathematical expression are given for all these relations.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org ➤ Epigenetic Control and Reprogramming-Induced Potential Landscapes of Gene Regulatory Networks: A Quantitative Theoretical Approach</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:17+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a quantitative dynamical mean-field/spin-glass-inspired theory for how epigenetic modifications (e.g., DNA methylation, histone marks) reshape gene-regulatory-network potential landscapes and stabilize or induce oscillatory gene-expression states, relevant to systems biology more than core origins-of-life.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24427v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: We develop an extended Dynamical Mean Field Theory framework to analyze gene regulatory networks (GRNs) incorporating epigenetic modifications. Building on the Hopfield network model analogy to spin glass systems, our approach introduces dynamic terms representing DNA methylation and histone modification to capture their regulatory influence on gene expression. The resulting formulation reduces high-dimensional GRN dynamics to effective stochastic equations, enabling the characterization of both stable and oscillatory states in epigenetically regulated systems. This framework provides a tractable and quantitative method for linking gene regulatory dynamics with epigenetic control, offering new theoretical insights into developmental processes and cell fate decisions.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org ➤ Dynamical Architectures of S-type Transiting Planets in Binaries II: A Dichotomy in Orbital Alignment of Small Planets in Close Binary Systems</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25332"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25332</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:18+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A TESS/Hipparcos–Gaia survey and hierarchical Bayesian analysis of S-type small planets in binary stars finds a strong two-population split in planet–binary orbital alignment (nearly aligned vs. highly misaligned/isotropic), with misalignment appearing only for wider-periastron (&gt;40 AU) stellar companions—relevant mainly as broad context for planetary system architectures that can influence long-term habitability.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2509.25332v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: Stellar multiplicity plays a crucial role in shaping planet formation and dynamical evolution. We present a survey of 54 TESS Objects of Interest (TOIs) within 300 pc that exhibit significant Hipparcos-Gaia astrometric accelerations. We identified 35 TOIs with stellar companions at projected separations between $0.1^{\prime\prime}$ to $2^{\prime\prime}$ (or $10-200$ AU). We also identified 12 TOIs that could host planetary-mass or brown dwarf companions, including 6 that are newly discovered. Furthermore, we perform three-dimensional orbital characterization for 12 binaries hosting confirmed planets or planet candidates, allowing us to constrain the line-of-sight mutual inclination, $\Delta I_{\mathrm{los}}$, between the planetary and binary orbits. Combining our sample with previous measurements, we apply Bayesian hierarchical analysis to a total of 26 binary systems with S-type transiting planets ($r_p&amp;lt;5R_{\oplus}$). Specifically, we fit the $\Delta I_{\mathrm{los}}$ distribution with both single (Rayleigh) and mixture models (two-component Rayleigh and Rayleigh-isotropic mixture). We find the mixture models are strongly favored ($\log Z\gtrsim13.9$, or $\approx$5$\sigma$), indicating the observed planet-binary $\Delta I_{\mathrm{los}}$ values likely originate from two underlying populations: one nearly aligned ($\sigma_1 = 2^{\circ}.4^{+0.7}_{-0.9}$) and one with more scattered mutual inclinations ($\sigma_2 = 23^{\circ}.6^{+8.8}_{-7.1}$). Alternatively, the misaligned systems can be equally well described by an isotropic distribution of inclinations. This observed dichotomy likely reflects different dynamical histories. Notably, the misaligned population only emerges in systems with stellar periastron distances $&amp;gt;40$ AU while systems with close-in or eccentric stellar companions (periastron distances $&amp;lt;40$ AU) preserve planet-binary alignment.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25332&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25332&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟡 astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org ➤ Seafloor Weathering and Stochastic Outgassing Unlikely to Significantly Shorten the Future Lifespan of Earth&#39;s Terrestrial Biosphere</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:19+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Using a coupled climate–weathering model, the authors find that even with potentially strong seafloor weathering feedbacks or unusually large stochastic CO2 outgassing variations, Earth’s terrestrial biosphere is still likely to persist for &gt;1 Gyr, with implications for long-term planetary habitability and exoplanet climate stability.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24538v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Current understanding suggests that as the Sun brightens in the far future, Earth&amp;#x27;s carbonate-silicate cycle will offset increasing temperatures by drawing CO$_2$ out of the atmosphere, ultimately leading to the extinction of all terrestrial plant life via either overheating or CO$_2$ starvation. Most previous estimates put the future lifespan of Earth&amp;#x27;s terrestrial biosphere at $\sim$1 billion yr, but recent work used a new coupled climate-continental weathering model with up-to-date parameter constraints to revise this estimate upward to 1.6-1.86 billion yr. In this study, we extend the model to examine the impacts of seafloor weathering and stochastic variations in CO$_2$ outgassing rates on the remaining lifespan of Earth&amp;#x27;s terrestrial biosphere. We find that if seafloor weathering has a stronger feedback than continental weathering and accounts for a large portion of global silicate weathering, then the remaining lifespan of the terrestrial biosphere can be shortened, but a lifespan of more than 1 billion yr (Gyr) remains likely. Similarly, stochastic fluctuations in outgassing rates can have a significant impact if the size of the fluctuations exceed those observed over the last 1 billion yr. The impact of weak seafloor weathering and lower variability stochasticity are minor. Our work provisionally supports a lengthened lifespan of Earth&amp;#x27;s terrestrial biosphere, suggests robustness of this lengthened lifespan to planetary parameters that may vary among exoplanets, and identifies seafloor weathering as a key process that requires further study and constraint.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.IT updates on arXiv.org ➤ Throughput Optimization in UAV-Mounted RIS under Jittering and Imperfect CSI via DRL</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24773"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24773</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:20+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops a deep reinforcement learning framework to optimize throughput in UAV-mounted reconfigurable intelligent surface wireless systems under jitter and imperfect channel estimation, which is unrelated to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24773v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs) mounted on unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) can reshape wireless propagation on-demand. However, their performance is sensitive to UAV jitter and cascaded channel uncertainty. This paper investigates a downlink multiple-input single-output UAV-mounted RIS system in which a ground multiple-antenna base station (BS) serves multiple single-antenna users under practical impairments. Our goal is to maximize the expected throughput under stochastic three-dimensional UAV jitter and imperfect cascaded channel state information (CSI) based only on the available channel estimates. This leads to a stochastic nonconvex optimization problem subject to a BS transmit power constraint and strict unit-modulus constraints on all RIS elements. To address this problem, we design a model-free deep reinforcement learning (DRL) framework with a contextual bandit formulation. A differentiable feasibility layer is utilized to map continuous actions to feasible solutions, while the reward is a Monte Carlo estimate of the expected throughput. We instantiate this framework with constrained variants of deep deterministic policy gradient (DDPG) and twin delayed deep deterministic policy gradient (TD3) that do not use target networks. Simulations show that the proposed algorithms yield higher throughput than conventional alternating optimization-based weighted minimum mean-square error (AO-WMMSE) baselines under severe jitter and low CSI quality. Across different scenarios, the proposed methods achieve performance that is either comparable to or slightly below the AO-WMMSE benchmark, based on sample average approximation (SAA) with a relative gap ranging from 0-12%. Moreover, the proposed DRL controllers achieve online inference times of 0.6 ms per decision versus roughly 370-550 ms for AO-WMMSE solvers.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24773&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24773&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.IT updates on arXiv.org ➤ A Uniform Pilot and Data Payload Optimization Framework for OTFS-Based ISAC</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24624"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24624</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:21+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper optimizes pilot and data power allocation for OTFS-based integrated sensing-and-communications (DFRC) signals, improving radar sidelobes and communication SINR, but it is unrelated to origins of life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24624v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: The orthogonal time frequency space (OTFS) signal is considered a promising solution for high-mobility wireless environments. It manages Doppler effects by utilizing delay-Doppler (DD) domain processing. However, the relatively long OTFS frame duration could introduce considerable sensing or communication latency when radar and communication are performed separately. By operating in a dual-functional radar and communication (DFRC) mode, the OTFS system performs sensing and data transmission simultaneously, thereby reducing the resulting latency. Nevertheless, the optimal OTFS DFRC signal strategy remains insufficiently explored. This paper investigates the optimal signal design for OTFS DFRC systems, focusing on pilot symbol design and data symbol power allocation. Specifically, we derive a channel capacity lower bound metric for communication that considers channel estimation errors in OTFS. For sensing, we derive an integrated sidelobe level (ISL), accounting for the randomness of the data symbols alongside the deterministic pilot symbols. Leveraging the above metrics, we formulate an optimization problem that balances radar and communication performance, and then solve it using an alternating optimization framework. We validate the proposed signal through numerical analysis and Monte Carlo simulations. Our analysis shows that OTFS DFRC enforces a deterministic pilot signal that is characterized by a concentrated peak in the DD domain, which furnishes a common structure in the DD domain facilitating sensing and channel estimation, with data multiplexed in other DD grids, thereby unifying sensing and communication within a single OTFS signal. Compared with conventional OTFS signals, the proposed OTFS DFRC signal expands the achievable sensing-communication performance region, delivering at least a 9.45 dB ISL suppression for sensing and a 4.82 dB SINR ratio gain for communication.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24624&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24624&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.IT updates on arXiv.org ➤ On maximum distance separable and completely regular codes</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24292"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24292</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:22+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper is a pure coding theory classification of when maximum distance separable (MDS) codes are completely regular or uniformly packed, with no apparent connection to origins of life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24292v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: We investigate when a maximum distance separable ($MDS$) code over $F_q$ is also completely regular ($CR$). For lengths $n=q+1$ and $n=q+2$ we provide a complete classification of the $MDS$ codes that are $CR$ or at least uniformly packed in the wide sense ($UPWS$). For the more restricted case $n\leq q$ with $q\leq 5$ we obtain a full classification (up to equivalence) of all nontrivial $MDS$ codes: there are none for $q=2$; only the ternary Hamming code for $q=3$; four nontrivial families for $q=4$; and exactly six linear $MDS$ codes for $q=5$ (three of which are $CR$ and one admits a self-dual version). Additionally, we close two gaps left open in a previous classification of self-dual $CR$ codes with covering radius $\rho\leq 3$: we precisely determine over which finite fields the $MDS$ self-dual completely regular codes with parameters $[2,1,2]_q$ and $[4,2,3]_q$ exist.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24292&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24292&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org ➤ A mini-review on combinatorial solutions to the Marcus-Lushnikov irreversible aggregation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:23+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Reviews a combinatorial state-enumeration framework for irreversible aggregation (Marcus–Lushnikov/Smoluchowski) with explicit results for several kernels and applications including aerosol growth and planetesimal formation, offering broadly relevant modeling tools but limited direct connection to prebiotic chemistry or origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.11459v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Over the past decade, a combinatorial framework for discrete, finite, and irreversibly aggregating systems has emerged. This work reviews its progress, practical applications, and limitations. We outline the approach&amp;#x27;s assumptions and foundations, based on direct enumeration of system states, contrasting with classical Smoluchowski and Marcus-Lushnikov methods. Using the constant kernel as an example, we derive combinatorial expressions for the average number of clusters of a given size and their standard deviation, and present the complete probability distribution for cluster counts. The method is then extended to several kernels (additive, product, linear-chain, condensation) by explicitly enumerating ways to form clusters of a given size. For general kernels, approximate solutions are obtained via recursive expressions, enabling predictions without explicit solutions. Applications to aerosol growth and planetesimal formation are demonstrated, with comparisons to numerical results. We summarize issues of validity and precision and propose open problems. The appendix includes partial Bell polynomials, generating functions, Lagrange inversion, potential applications, and links between combinatorial and scaling solutions of the Smoluchowski equation.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 q-bio.MN updates on arXiv.org ➤ Epigenetic Control and Reprogramming-Induced Potential Landscapes of Gene Regulatory Networks: A Quantitative Theoretical Approach</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:24+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a quantitative dynamical mean-field framework for gene regulatory networks with epigenetic modifications (DNA methylation/histone effects), offering systems-level insight into cell-fate landscapes but with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24427v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: We develop an extended Dynamical Mean Field Theory framework to analyze gene regulatory networks (GRNs) incorporating epigenetic modifications. Building on the Hopfield network model analogy to spin glass systems, our approach introduces dynamic terms representing DNA methylation and histone modification to capture their regulatory influence on gene expression. The resulting formulation reduces high-dimensional GRN dynamics to effective stochastic equations, enabling the characterization of both stable and oscillatory states in epigenetically regulated systems. This framework provides a tractable and quantitative method for linking gene regulatory dynamics with epigenetic control, offering new theoretical insights into developmental processes and cell fate decisions.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org ➤ EMPEROR I. Exoplanet MCMC parallel tempering for RV orbit retrieval</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:25+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces EMPEROR, an open-source Python framework using nested sampling and adaptive parallel-tempering MCMC to improve radial-velocity exoplanet orbit retrieval and noise-model comparison, but with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2511.05331v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: We present EMPEROR, an open-source Python framework designed for efficient exoplanet detection and characterisation with radial velocities (RV). EMPEROR integrates Dynamic Nested Sampling (DNS) and Adaptive Parallel Tempering (APT) Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), supporting multiple noise models such as Gaussian Processes (GPs) and Moving Averages (MA). The framework enables systematic model comparison using statistical metrics, including Bayesian evidence ($\ln{\mathcal{Z}}$) and Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC), while providing automated, publish-ready visualisations. EMPEROR is evaluated across three distinct systems to assess its capabilities in different detection scenarios. Sampling performance, model selection, and the search for Earth-mass planets are evaluated in data for 51 Pegasi, HD 55693 and Barnard&amp;#x27;s Star (GJ 699). For 51 Pegasi, APT achieves an effective sampling increase over DNS by a factor 3.76, while retrieving tighter parameter estimates. For HD 55693 the stellar rotation $P_{\text{rot}}=29.72^{+0.01}_{-0.02}$ and magnetic cycle $P_{\text{mag}}=2557.0^{+70.1}_{-36.7}$ are recovered, while demonstrating the sensitivity of $\ln{\mathcal{Z}}$ to prior selection. For Barnard&amp;#x27;s star, several noise models are compared, and the confirmed planet parameters are successfully retrieved with all of them. The best model shows a period of 3.1536$\pm$0.0003~d, minimum mass of 0.38$\pm$0.03 M$_{\rm{\oplus}}$, and semi-major axis of 0.02315$\pm$0.00039~AU. Purely statistical inference might be insufficient on its own for robust exoplanet detection. Effective methodologies must integrate domain knowledge, heuristic criteria, and multi-faceted model comparisons. The versatility of EMPEROR in handling diverse noise structures, its systematic model selection, and its improved performance make it a valuable tool for RV exoplanetary studies.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cs.IT updates on arXiv.org ➤ The Generalization Error of Supervised Machine Learning Algorithms</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12030"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12030</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:26+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces an information-theoretic “method of gaps” to derive exact generalization-error expressions for supervised machine-learning algorithms, with no direct connection to origins-of-life, astrobiology, or biosignature/habitability studies.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2411.12030v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: In this paper, the method of gaps, a technique for deriving closed-form expressions in terms of information measures for the generalization error of supervised machine learning algorithms is introduced. The method relies on the notion of \emph{gaps}, which characterize the variation of the expected empirical risk (when either the model or dataset is kept fixed) with respect to changes in the probability measure on the varying parameter (either the dataset or the model, respectively). This distinction results in two classes of gaps: Algorithm-driven gaps (fixed dataset) and data-driven gaps (fixed model). In general, the method relies on two central observations: $(i)$~The generalization error is the expectation of an algorithm-driven gap or a data-driven gap. In the first case, the expectation is with respect to a measure on the datasets; and in the second case, with respect to a measure on the models. $(ii)$~Both, algorithm-driven gaps and data-driven gaps exhibit closed-form expressions in terms of relative entropies. In particular, algorithm-driven gaps involve a Gibbs probability measure on the set of models, which represents a supervised Gibbs algorithm. Alternatively, data-driven gaps involve a worst-case data-generating (WCDG) probability measure on the set of data points, which is also a Gibbs probability measure. Interestingly, such Gibbs measures, which are exogenous to the analysis of generalization, place both the supervised Gibbs algorithm and the WCDG probability measure as natural references for the analysis of supervised learning algorithms. All existing exact expressions for the generalization error of supervised machine learning algorithms can be obtained with the proposed method. Also, this method allows obtaining numerous new exact expressions, which allows establishing connections with other areas in statistics.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12030&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12030&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 cs.IT updates on arXiv.org ➤ Information Physics of Intelligence: Unifying Logical Depth and Entropy under Thermodynamic Constraints</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19156"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19156</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:27+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Proposes a thermodynamically grounded framework linking Shannon entropy and computational (logical) depth via a new &#39;Derivation Entropy&#39; metric, offering a high-level perspective on energetic constraints that could analogically inform discussions of evolution/complexification but is not directly about prebiotic chemistry or origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2511.19156v4 Announce Type: replace Abstract: The rapid scaling of artificial intelligence models has revealed a fundamental tension between model capacity (storage) and inference efficiency (computation). While classical information theory focuses on transmission and storage limits, it lacks a unified physical framework to quantify the thermodynamic costs of generating information from compressed laws versus retrieving it from memory. In this paper, we propose a theoretical framework that treats information processing as an enabling mapping from ontological states to carrier states. We introduce a novel metric, Derivation Entropy, which quantifies the effective work required to compute a target state from a given logical depth. By analyzing the interplay between Shannon entropy (storage) and computational complexity (time/energy), we demonstrate the existence of a critical phase transition point. Below this threshold, memory retrieval is thermodynamically favorable; above it, generative computation becomes the optimal strategy. This &amp;quot;Energy-Time-Space&amp;quot; conservation law provides a physical explanation for the efficiency of generative models and offers a rigorous mathematical bound for designing next-generation, energy-efficient AI architectures. Our findings suggest that the minimization of Derivation Entropy is a governing principle for the evolution of both biological and artificial intelligence.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19156&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19156&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org ➤ Constraints on the perfect phylogeny mixture model and their effect on reducing degeneracy</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24930"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24930</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:28+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical/computational study of degeneracy in perfect phylogeny mixture models (motivated by tumor evolution) that has only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions via general evolutionary inference methodology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24930v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: The perfect phylogeny mixture (PPM) model is useful due to its simplicity and applicability in scenarios where mutations can be assumed to accumulate monotonically over time. It is the underlying model in many tools that have been used, for example, to infer phylogenetic trees for tumor evolution and reconstruction. Unfortunately, the PPM model gives rise to substantial ambiguity -- in that many different phylogenetic trees can explain the same observed data -- even in the idealized setting where data are observed perfectly, i.e. fully and without noise. This ambiguity has been studied in this perfect setting by Pradhan et al. 2018, which proposed a procedure to bound the number of solutions given a fixed instance of observation data. Beyond this, studies have been primarily empirical. Recent work (Myers et al. 2019) proposed adding extra constraints to the PPM model to tackle ambiguity. In this paper, we first show that the extra constraints of Myers et al. 2019, called longitudinal constraints (LC), often fail to reduce the number of distinct trees that explain the observations. We then propose novel alternative constraints to limit solution ambiguity and study their impact when the data are observed perfectly. Unlike the analysis in Pradhan et al. 2018, our theoretical results regarding both the inefficacy of the LC and the extent to which our new constrains reduce ambiguity are not tied to a single observation instance. Rather, our theorems hold over large ensembles of possible inference problems. To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to study degeneracy in the PPM model in this ensemble-based theoretical framework.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24930&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24930&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org ➤ Binary Galton-Watson trees with mutations</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10951"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10951</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops exact (non-approximate) multitype Galton–Watson branching-process results for mutation/reversion dynamics, offering broadly relevant mathematical tools for modeling evolutionary diversification but with no explicit origins-of-life or prebiotic chemistry focus.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2501.10951v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: We consider a multitype Galton-Watson process that allows for the mutation and reversion of individual types in discrete and continuous time. In this setting, we explicitly compute the time evolution of quantities such as the mean and distributions of different types. This allows us in particular to estimate the proportions of different types in the long run, as well as the distribution of the first time of occurrence of a given type as the tree size or time increases. Our approach relies on the recursive computation of the joint distribution of types conditionally to the value of the total progeny. In comparison with the literature on related multitype models, we do not rely on approximations.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10951&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10951&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org ➤ Emergence of 3D Superconformal Ising Criticality on the Fuzzy Sphere</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25054"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25054</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:30+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops a non-perturbative condensed-matter/high-energy framework for realizing 3D supersymmetric conformal criticality on a fuzzy sphere, with no direct connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.25054v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: Supersymmetric conformal field theories (SCFTs) form a unique subset of quantum field theories which provide powerful insights into strongly coupled critical phenomena. Here, we present a microscopic and non-perturbative realization of the three-dimensional $\mathcal{N}=1$ superconformal Ising critical point, based on a Yukawa-type coupling between a 3D Ising CFT and a gauged Majorana fermion. Using the recently developed fuzzy sphere regularization, we directly extract the scaling dimensions of low-lying operators via the state-operator correspondence. At the critical point, we demonstrate conformal multiplet structure together with the hallmark of emergent spacetime supersymmetry through characteristic relations between fermionic and bosonic operators. Moreover, by tuning the Yukawa coupling, we explicitly track the evolution of operator spectra from the decoupled Ising-Majorana fixed point to the interacting superconformal fixed point, revealing renormalization-group flow at the operator level. Our results establish a controlled, non-perturbative microscopic route to 3D SCFTs.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25054&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25054&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org ➤ Randomization Times under Quantum Chaotic Hamiltonian Evolution</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25074"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25074</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:31+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This arXiv preprint studies how generic quantum-chaotic Hamiltonians can rapidly generate near–Haar-random behavior from simple initial states, a result relevant to quantum statistical mechanics and information theory but only tangential to origins-of-life research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.25074v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Randomness generation through quantum-chaotic evolution underpins foundational questions in statistical mechanics and applications across quantum information science, including benchmarking, tomography, metrology, and demonstrations of quantum computational advantage. While statistical mechanics successfully captures the temporal averages of local observables, understanding randomness at the level of higher statistical moments remains a daunting challenge, with analytic progress largely confined to random quantum circuit models or fine-tuned systems exhibiting space-time duality. Here we study how much randomness can be dynamically generated by generic quantum-chaotic evolution under physical, non-random Hamiltonians. Combining theoretical insights with numerical simulations, we show that for broad classes of initially unentangled states, the dynamics become effectively Haar-random well before the system can ergodically explore the physically accessible Hilbert space. Both local and highly nonlocal observables, including entanglement measures, equilibrate to their Haar expectation values and fluctuations on polynomial timescales with remarkably high numerical precision, and with the fastest randomization occurring in regions of parameter space previously identified as maximally chaotic. Interestingly, this effective randomization can occur on timescales linear in system size, suggesting that the sub-ballistic growth of Renyi entropies typically observed in systems with conservation laws can be bypassed in non-random Hamiltonians with an appropriate choice of initial conditions.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25074&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25074&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org ➤ The tournament ratchet&#39;s clicktime process, and metastability in a Moran model</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24779"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24779</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:32+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A rigorous mathematical analysis of Muller&#39;s ratchet under tournament selection, proving Poissonian click times in the slow-clicking regime via metastability results for a two-type Moran model—relevant mainly as general evolutionary theory rather than direct origins-of-life chemistry or protocell work.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24779v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: Muller&amp;#x27;s ratchet, in its prototype version, models a haploid, asexual population whose size~$N$ is constant over the generations. Slightly deleterious mutations are acquired along the lineages at a constant rate, and individuals carrying less mutations have a selective advantage. In the classical variant, an individual&amp;#x27;s selective advantage is proportional to the difference between the population average and the individual&amp;#x27;s mutation load, whereas in the ratchet with {\em tournament selection} only the signs of the differences of the individual mutation loads matter. In a parameter regime which leads to slow clicking (i.e. to a loss of the currently fittest class at a rate $\ll 1/N$) we prove that the rescaled process of click times of the tournament ratchet converges as $N\to \infty$ to a Poisson process. Central ingredients in the proof are a thorough analysis of the metastable behaviour of a two-type Moran model with selection and deleterious mutation (which describes the size of the fittest class up to its extinction time) and a lower estimate on the size of the new fittest class at a clicktime.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24779&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24779&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org ➤ Assessment of First-Principles Methods in Modeling the Melting Properties of Water</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:33+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Benchmarks several first-principles water models (DFT functionals vs MB-pol) for melting-point-related properties using PIMD+machine-learning potentials, finding MB-pol agrees well with experiment while common DFT functionals systematically mis-handle nuclear quantum effects—relevant to aqueous habitability contexts but not directly focused on origins-of-life chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.23940v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: First-principles simulations have played a crucial role in deepening our understanding of the thermodynamic properties of water, and machine learning potentials (MLPs) trained on these first-principles data widen the range of accessible properties. However, the capabilities of different first-principles methods are not yet fully understood due to the lack of systematic benchmarks, the underestimation of the uncertainties introduced by MLPs, and the neglect of nuclear quantum effects (NQEs). Here, we systematically assess first-principles methods by calculating key melting properties using path integral molecular dynamics (PIMD) driven by Deep Potential (DP) models trained on data from density functional theory (DFT) with SCAN, revPBE0-D3, SCAN0 and revPBE-D3 functionals, as well as from the MB-pol potential. We find that MB-pol is in qualitatively good agreement with the experiment in all properties tested, whereas the four DFT functionals incorrectly predict that NQEs increase the melting temperature. SCAN and SCAN0 slightly underestimate the density change between water and ice upon melting, but revPBE-D3 and revPBE0-D3 severely underestimate it. Moreover, SCAN and SCAN0 correctly predict that the maximum liquid density occurs at a temperature higher than the melting point, while revPBE-D3 and revPBE0-D3 predict the opposite behavior. Our results highlight limitations in widely used first-principles methods and call for a reassessment of their predictive power in aqueous systems.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org ➤ Steering chiral active Brownian motion via stochastic position-orientation resetting</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12223"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12223</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:34+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This theoretical active-matter study shows that stochastic position-orientation resetting can disrupt circular (chiral) swimming to tune transport regimes, offering chirality-relevant physics but only indirect relevance to origins-of-life problems.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2508.12223v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Guiding active motion is important for targeted delivery, sensing, and search tasks. Many active systems exhibit circular swimming, ubiquitous in chemical, physical, and biological systems, that biases motion and reduces transport efficiency. We show that stochastic position-orientation resetting can overcome these limitations in two-dimensional chiral active Brownian particles by interrupting circular motion, resulting in tunable dynamics. When resets are infrequent compared to chiral rotation, the steady-state mean-squared displacement varies non-monotonically with rotational diffusion. Steady state excess kurtosis and orientation autocorrelation yields spatiotemporal state diagram comprising three states: an activity-dominated chiral state, and two resetting-dominated states with and without chiral rotation; in contrast, the achiral(or non-chiral) counterpart supports only the resetting-dominated state without chiral rotation. Chirality thus enriches the dynamical landscape, enabling tunable transitions between transport modes absent in achiral systems. A simple reset protocol can therefore transform chiral active dynamics and offer a practical strategy for optimizing search and transport in circle swimmers.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12223&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12223&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Fast Poisson brackets and constraint algebras in canonical gravity</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25007"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25007</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:35+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a computer-algebra package for efficiently computing Poisson brackets and constraint algebras in canonical gravity, with tests on GR and modified gravity, but it has no direct connection to origins-of-life or astrobiology topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.25007v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: In the study of alternative or extended theories of gravity, Dirac&amp;#x27;s Hamiltonian constraint algorithm is invaluable for enumerating the propagating modes and gauge symmetries. For gravity, this canonical approach is frequently applied as a means for finding pathologies such as strongly coupled modes; more generally it facilitates the reconstruction of gauge symmetries and the quantization of gauge theories. For gravity, however, the algorithm can become notoriously arduous to implement. We present a simple computer algebra package for efficiently computing Poisson brackets and reconstructing constraint algebras. The tools are stress-tested against pure general relativity and modified gravity, including the order reduction of general relativity at two loops.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25007&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25007&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org ➤ Lack-of-fit reduction in the path-integral formalism</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:36+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces a path-integral/Onsager–Machlup formulation of lack-of-fit reduction in non-equilibrium thermodynamics, showing how coarse-graining can yield emergent irreversibility and extending information-geometric measures to maximum-entropy settings (including non-Boltzmann entropies).</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2506.20242v3 Announce Type: replace Abstract: We present a new formulation of the lack-of-fit reduction in non-equilibrium thermodynamics using the path-integral formalism. The formulation is based on the Onsager-Machlup variational principle, and it allows us to find reduced dynamical equations by minimizing information discrepancy with respect to the detailed evolution. The reduced evolution consists of a Hamiltonian vector field and a gradient flow. The reduction method is illustrated on the Kac-Zwanzig model, where we show how irreversibility emerges from purely Hamiltonian evolution by ignoring some degrees of freedom. We also show how to generalize the Fisher information matrix and Kullback-Leibler divergence between two probability distributions to the case when the two distributions are related by the principle of maximum entropy, even in the case when the entropy is not of Boltzmann-Gibbs type (for instance Tsallis-Havrda-Charvat entropy).
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Simple and general unitarity conserving numerical real time propagators of time dependent Schr\&#34;odinger equation based on Magnus expansion</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:37+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops unitarity-preserving Magnus-expansion numerical propagators for time-dependent Schrödinger dynamics, a broadly useful quantum simulation tool but not directly focused on origins-of-life or astrobiology topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2312.01115v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Magnus expansion (ME) provides a general way to expand the real-time propagator of a time-dependent Hamiltonian within the exponential such that the unitarity is satisfied at any order. We use this property and explicit integration of Lagrange interpolation formulas for the time-dependent Hamiltonian within each time interval and derive approximations that preserve unitarity for the differential time evolution operators of general time-dependent Hamiltonians. The resulting second-order approximation is the same as using the average of Hamiltonians for two end points of time. We identify three fourth-order approximations involving commutators of Hamiltonians at different times and also derive a sixth-order expression. A test of these approximations along with other available expressions for a two-state time-dependent Hamiltonian with sinusoidal time dependences provides information on the relative performance of these approximations and suggests that the derived expressions can serve as useful numerical tools for time evolution in time-resolved spectroscopy, quantum control, quantum sensing, real-time ab initio quantum dynamics, and open system quantum dynamics.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Pair Space in Classical Mechanics III. Some Four-Body Central Configurations</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:38+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This mathematical physics paper classifies certain symmetric central configurations in the classical four-body problem using a pair-space formalism, with no direct connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiological habitability.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.23730v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: We study central configurations in the four body problem, i.e., configurations in which the forces on all the bodies point to a fixed, single point in space. The newly formulated pair-space formalism yields a set of vectorial equations that fully characterize such configurations. We investigate a sub-class of solutions in which at least two pairs of inter-body distances are equal. The only such non-collinear configurations are the tetrahedron (the unique non-planar configuration), kites and the isosceles trapezium. The specific shapes (internal angles) are determined by the ratio of the masses of the bodies. Mathematical expression are given for all these relations.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23730&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Classical integrability in 2D and asymptotic symmetries</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24833"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24833</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:39+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Lecture notes on classical integrability, asymptotic symmetries, and conserved charges in 3D Chern–Simons theory (with examples like KdV/AKNS and near-horizon 3D gravity), with no direct connection to origins of life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24833v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: These lecture notes are a contribution to the proceedings of the school &amp;quot;Geometric, Algebraic and Topological Methods for Quantum Field Theory&amp;quot;, held in Villa de Leyva, Colombia, from 31st of July to 9th of August 2023. Its intention is to put together several basic tools of classical integrability and contrast them with those available in the formulation of asymptotic symmetries and the definition of canonical charges in gauge theories. We consider as a working example the Chern-Simons theory in 3D dimensions, motivated by its various applications in condensed matter physics, gravity, and black hole physics. We review basic aspects of the canonical formulation, symplectic geometry, Liouville integrability, and Lax Pairs. We define the Hamiltonian formulation of the Chern-Simons action and the canonical generators of the gauge symmetries, which are surface integrals that subject to non-trivial boundary conditions, realize transformations that do change the physical state, namely large (or improper gauge transformations). We propose asymptotic conditions that realize an infinite set of abelian conserved charges associated with integral models. We review two different cases: the Korteweg-de Vries equation for its connection with the Virasoro algebra and fluid dynamics, and the Ablowitz-Kaup-Newell-Segur (AKNS) hierarchy, as it embeds an infinite class of non-linear notable integrable evolution equations. We propose a concrete example for gravity in 3D with $\Lambda&amp;lt;0$, where we find a near-horizon asymptotic dynamics. We finalize offering some insights on the initial value problem, its connection with integrable systems and flat connections. We study some properties of the Monodromy matrix and recover the infinite KdV charges from the trace invariants extracted from the Monodromy evolution equation that can be written in a Lax form.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24833&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24833&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org ➤ A mini-review on combinatorial solutions to the Marcus-Lushnikov irreversible aggregation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:40+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Mini-review of a combinatorial state-enumeration framework for irreversible aggregation (Marcus–Lushnikov/Smoluchowski) with worked kernels and applications including aerosol growth and planetesimal formation, offering broadly relevant tools for self-assembly/aggregation modeling but not directly focused on origins-of-life chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.11459v3 Announce Type: replace Abstract: Over the past decade, a combinatorial framework for discrete, finite, and irreversibly aggregating systems has emerged. This work reviews its progress, practical applications, and limitations. We outline the approach&amp;#x27;s assumptions and foundations, based on direct enumeration of system states, contrasting with classical Smoluchowski and Marcus-Lushnikov methods. Using the constant kernel as an example, we derive combinatorial expressions for the average number of clusters of a given size and their standard deviation, and present the complete probability distribution for cluster counts. The method is then extended to several kernels (additive, product, linear-chain, condensation) by explicitly enumerating ways to form clusters of a given size. For general kernels, approximate solutions are obtained via recursive expressions, enabling predictions without explicit solutions. Applications to aerosol growth and planetesimal formation are demonstrated, with comparisons to numerical results. We summarize issues of validity and precision and propose open problems. The appendix includes partial Bell polynomials, generating functions, Lagrange inversion, potential applications, and links between combinatorial and scaling solutions of the Smoluchowski equation.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Hawksmoor&#39;s Ceiling, Mercator&#39;s Projection and the Roman Pantheon</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22327"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22327</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:41+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Uses differential geometry and conformal (Mercator-like) mappings to explain/coherently model square coffer patterns on vaulted ceilings (Hawksmoor’s Buttery and the Roman Pantheon), with no connection to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.22327v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: The ceiling of the Buttery in All Souls College, Oxford, designed by the English Baroque architect Nicholas Hawksmoor, has a vaulted form on an oval base. It is coffered with an array of approximately square sunken lacunaria, whose sizes and positions vary so as to accommodate the constraints of the curved surface and its boundaries. A similar design appears in the dome of the Roman Pantheon. Using methods of differential geometry, we hypothesise that these cofferings should be the images under conformal mappings of regular square tilings of a rectangle or finite cylinder. This guarantees that the coffer ribs meet exactly at right angles and the coffers are close to being square. These mappings are simply the inverse of Mercator&amp;#x27;s projection of the curved surface onto a plane. For a ceiling which is a general surface of revolution, we derive formulae for the dimensions and location of each coffer. Our results, taking into account camera distortion, are in excellent agreement with photographs of the Hawksmoor ceiling and the Pantheon dome, as well as with recent direct measurements of the latter. We also describe a protocol by which Hawksmoor&amp;#x27;s ceiling might have been constructed without advanced mathematics.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22327&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22327&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Towards mechanistic understanding in a data-driven weather model: internal activations reveal interpretable physical features</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24440"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24440</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:42+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Uses sparse autoencoders and intervention-based interpretability to identify physically meaningful internal features (e.g., cyclones, atmospheric rivers, seasonal/diurnal modes) in the GraphCast data-driven weather model, improving transparency but with minimal direct relevance to origins-of-life research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24440v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: Large data-driven physics models like DeepMind&amp;#x27;s weather model GraphCast have empirically succeeded in parameterizing time operators for complex dynamical systems with an accuracy reaching or in some cases exceeding that of traditional physics-based solvers. Unfortunately, how these data-driven models perform computations is largely unknown and whether their internal representations are interpretable or physically consistent is an open question. Here, we adapt tools from interpretability research in Large Language Models to analyze intermediate computational layers in GraphCast, leveraging sparse autoencoders to discover interpretable features in the neuron space of the model. We uncover distinct features on a wide range of length and time scales that correspond to tropical cyclones, atmospheric rivers, diurnal and seasonal behavior, large-scale precipitation patterns, specific geographical coding, and sea-ice extent, among others. We further demonstrate how the precise abstraction of these features can be probed via interventions on the prediction steps of the model. As a case study, we sparsely modify a feature corresponding to tropical cyclones in GraphCast and observe interpretable and physically consistent modifications to evolving hurricanes. Such methods offer a window into the black-box behavior of data-driven physics models and are a step towards realizing their potential as trustworthy predictors and scientifically valuable tools for discovery.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24440&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24440&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Enhanced premelting at the ice-rubber interface using all-atom molecular dynamics simulation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:43+00:00</updated>
    <summary>All-atom MD simulations show that hydrophobic styrene–butadiene rubber can enhance structural disorder and premelting at the ice basal face while suppressing water mobility via polymer confinement, offering only indirect Origins-of-Life relevance via ice–organic interfacial physics in cold environments.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2508.20448v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: The ice-rubber interface is critical in applications such as tires and shoe outsoles, yet its molecular tribology remains unclear. Using all-atom molecular dynamics simulations, we studied premelting layers at the basal face of ice in contact with styrene-butadiene rubber from 254 to 269 K. Despite its hydrophobicity, rubber enhances structural disorder of interfacial water, promoting premelting. In contrast, water mobility is suppressed by confinement from polymer chains, leading to glassy dynamics distinct from the ice-vapor interface. Near the melting point, rubber chains become more flexible and penetrate the premelting layer, forming a mixed rubber-water region that couples the dynamics of both components. These results suggest that nanoscale roughness and morphology of hydrophobic polymers disrupt ice hydrogen-bond networks, thereby enhancing premelting. Our findings provide molecular-level insight into ice slipperiness and inform the design of polymer materials with controlled ice adhesion and friction.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Martini Mapper: An Automated Fragment-Based Framework for Developing Coarse-Grained Models within the Martini 3 Framework</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:44+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces an automated SMILES-to–Martini 3 coarse-graining mapper validated against octanol–water partitioning data, a generally useful simulation tool that could indirectly support origins-of-life studies (e.g., protocell/membrane self-assembly modeling) but is not itself OoL-focused.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2511.11859v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Coarse-graining (CG) reduces molecular details to extend the time and length scales of molecular dynamics simulations to microseconds and micrometers. However, the CG approaches have long been limited by the difficulty of constructing both accurate and transferable models efficiently, considering the large diversity of chemical structures of materials. Among CG force fields, Martini is the most widely used, as it retains essential chemical features while offering substantial computational efficiency. Its most recent version, Martini 3, expands chemical resolution through a much broader bead set, particularly for small molecules. However, this flexibility also complicates the mapping of organic molecules because of context-dependent rules and the lack of standardized procedures. To address this issue, we present an automated framework that builds Martini 3 models directly from SMILES (Simplified Molecular Input Line Entry System) strings by combining a curated bead dictionary with a hierarchical, rule-based algorithm. Our framework, Martini Mapper, generated Martini 3 models for more than 5,000 molecules across four chemically diverse datasets. A curated subset of 1,081 mapped structures was benchmarked through octanol-water free-energy ($\Delta G_{OW}$) and partition-coefficient ($\log P$) calculations, yielding strong agreement with experimental values. The workflow can also map large molecules containing up to 126 heavy atoms, exceeding the capabilities of existing automated approaches. The algorithm and the complete set of more than 5,000 mapped itp/top files are available at the \href{https://github.com/eliobaby/Martini_mapping}{Martini Mapper}. Our framework, therefore, enables systematic and scalable Martini 3 structures for high-throughput simulations relevant to drug discovery and materials design.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ On spectral equations for an evolution operator of a $q$-oscillator lattice</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24043"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24043</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:45+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Mathematical-physics work deriving spectral/Bethe-Ansatz equations for a unitary evolution operator in a 2D q-oscillator Kagomé lattice, with no direct connection to origins-of-life or astrobiology beyond the generic term “evolution.”}</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24043v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: We propose a set of algebraic equations describing eigenvalues and eigenstates of a relativistic evolution operator for a two-dimensional $q$-oscillator Kagom\&amp;#x27;e lattice. Evolution operator is constructed with the help of $q$-oscillator solution of the Tetrahedron Equation. We focus on the unitary regime of the evolution operator, so our results are related to 3d integrable systems of the quantum mechanics. Our conjecture is based on a two-dimensional lattice version of the coordinate Bethe-Ansatz.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24043&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24043&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Generative forecasting with joint probability models</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24446"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24446</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:46+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Proposes a joint-probability generative modeling framework for forecasting chaotic dynamical systems with uncertainty metrics, offering generally useful methodology but with no direct connection to origins-of-life chemistry, prebiotic processes, or astrobiological biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24446v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: Chaotic dynamical systems exhibit strong sensitivity to initial conditions and often contain unresolved multiscale processes, making deterministic forecasting fundamentally limited. Generative models offer an appealing alternative by learning distributions over plausible system evolutions; yet, most existing approaches focus on next-step conditional prediction rather than the structure of the underlying dynamics. In this work, we reframe forecasting as a fully generative problem by learning the joint probability distribution of lagged system states over short temporal windows and obtaining forecasts through marginalization. This new perspective allows the model to capture nonlinear temporal dependencies, represent multistep trajectory segments, and produce next-step predictions consistent with the learned joint distribution. We also introduce a general, model-agnostic training and inference framework for joint generative forecasting and show how it enables assessment of forecast robustness and reliability using three complementary uncertainty quantification metrics (ensemble variance, short-horizon autocorrelation, and cumulative Wasserstein drift), without access to ground truth. We evaluate the performance of the proposed method on two canonical chaotic dynamical systems, the Lorenz-63 system and the Kuramoto-Sivashinsky equation, and show that joint generative models yield improved short-term predictive skill, preserve attractor geometry, and achieve substantially more accurate long-range statistical behaviour than conventional conditional next-step models.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24446&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24446&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Lack-of-fit reduction in the path-integral formalism</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:47+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops a path-integral/Onsager–Machlup framework for reducing non-equilibrium dynamics, showing how irreversible behavior can emerge from underlying Hamiltonian evolution when degrees of freedom are coarse-grained.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2506.20242v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: We present a new formulation of the lack-of-fit reduction in non-equilibrium thermodynamics using the path-integral formalism. The formulation is based on the Onsager-Machlup variational principle, and it allows us to find reduced dynamical equations by minimizing information discrepancy with respect to the detailed evolution. The reduced evolution consists of a Hamiltonian vector field and a gradient flow. The reduction method is illustrated on the Kac-Zwanzig model, where we show how irreversibility emerges from purely Hamiltonian evolution by ignoring some degrees of freedom. We also show how to generalize the Fisher information matrix and Kullback-Leibler divergence between two probability distributions to the case when the two distributions are related by the principle of maximum entropy, even in the case when the entropy is not of Boltzmann-Gibbs type (for instance Tsallis-Havrda-Charvat entropy).
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20242&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Generalized Wigner-Smith theory for perturbations at exceptional and diabolic point degeneracies</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05039"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05039</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:48+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical non-Hermitian wave-scattering perturbation framework for exceptional/diabolic point resonance splitting with no direct connection to origins-of-life chemistry, prebiotic processes, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2508.05039v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Spectral degeneracies, including diabolic (DP) and exceptional (EP) points, exhibit unique sensitivity to external perturbations, enabling powerful control and engineering of wave phenomena. We present a residue-based perturbation theory that quantifies complex resonance splitting of DP and EP type spectral degeneracies using generalized Wigner-Smith operators. We validate our theory using both analytic Hamiltonian models and numerical electromagnetic simulations, demonstrating excellent agreement across a range of cases. Our approach accurately predicts degenerate resonance splitting using only scattering data, offering a powerful framework for precision tuning, inverse design, and practical exploitation of non-Hermitian phenomena.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05039&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05039&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟢 physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Protocellular energetics: Free energy estimates for all metabolic, self-assembly and vesicle fission processes</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24095"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24095</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:49+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Quantifies free-energy changes across an entire protocell lifecycle—metabolism, self-assembly, membrane bending, and vesicle fission—providing a thermodynamic accounting relevant to minimal-cell origins-of-life models.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24095v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: As minimal cells or protocells are dramatically simpler than modern unicells it is possible to quantitatively estimate free energy changes for every process in the lifecycle of a protocell and compare these with estimates of the free energy changes for lifecycles in modern unicells. We present quantitative estimates of all metabolic changes in part by new density function theory (DFT) estimations, in part by compiling previously measured or estimated free energy changes, and in part by new thermodynamic calculations for all self-assembly, vesicle bending, and fission energies.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24095&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24095&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Optically Controlled Skyrmion Number Current</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11209"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11209</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:50+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Condensed-matter theory paper on optically driven magnetic skyrmion dynamics and skyrmion-number currents, with no direct connection to prebiotic chemistry, abiogenesis, habitability, or origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2508.11209v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: We propose a mechanism to control the motion of magnetic Skyrmions through the generation of a Skyrmion number current. This current is induced and tuned by an explicitly time-dependent Hamiltonian that includes a Zeeman term arising from the interaction between the spin system and circularly polarized light. To capture the effect, we apply a first-order perturbation method to the Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert equation, using a breathing Skyrmion ansatz based on the Belavin-Polyakov profile. This approach reveals that the time-dependent deformation of the Skyrmion boundary produces an anisotropic breathing mode, which in turn generates a nonzero Skyrmion number current. The resulting dynamics in momentum space form a limit cycle, whose characteristics depend on the external magnetic field amplitude, the Heisenberg exchange coupling, and the Gilbert damping constant. Our formulation not only clarifies the topological origin of optically driven Skyrmion motion but also points to Skyrmion number currents as a low-dissipation alternative to electric currents for efficient Skyrmion control.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11209&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11209&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Mechanical properties of chiral actin filaments</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24154"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24154</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:51+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Coarse-grained mesoscale modeling shows how helicity/chirality shape actin filament mechanics and motor-driven torques, offering general tools for chiral filament dynamics but with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24154v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: The mechanical properties of actin filaments are essential to their biological functions. Here, we introduce a highly coarse-grained model of actin filaments that preserves helicity and chirality while enabling mesoscale simulations. The framework is implemented in Cytosim, an open-source cytoskeleton simulation platform. We can predict and finely control the shape and mechanical properties of this helical filament, that can be matched to experimental values. Using this model, we investigated the role of filament chirality in motor-driven dynamics. We first show that in two different experimental configurations, motor movement along a helical filament results in a chiral motion of the filament. In a bundle of helical filaments, dimeric motors exert torques on each filament, inducing collective behaviors in the bundle such as rotation, coiling, and helical buckling, reminiscent of those observed in filopodia. Together, these results demonstrate the central role of helicity and chirality in actin mechanics and motor-driven dynamics, and establish our framework as a powerful tool for mesoscale simulations. This framework can also be used for other helical filaments beyond actin.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24154&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24154&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Ab Initio Melting Properties of Water and Ice from Machine Learning Potentials</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23939"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23939</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:52+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Uses path-integral MD with machine-learning potentials to predict water/ice melting behavior and isotope nuclear-quantum effects, benchmarking DFT-based models against MB-pol to improve physical fidelity of aqueous simulations relevant to habitability contexts.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.23939v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Liquid water exhibits several important anomalous properties in the vicinity of the melting temperature ($T_{\mathrm{m}}$) of ice Ih, including a higher density than ice and a density maximum at 4~$^{\circ}$C. Experimentally, an isotope effect on $T_{\mathrm{m}}$ is observed: the melting temperature of H$_2$O is approximately 4~K lower than that of D$_2$O. This difference can only be explained by nuclear quantum effects (NQEs), which can be accurately captured using path integral molecular dynamics (PIMD). Here we run PIMD simulations driven by Deep Potential (DP) models trained on data from density functional theory (DFT) based on SCAN, revPBE0-D3, SCAN0, and revPBE-D3 and a DP model trained on the MB-pol potential. We calculate the \tm of ice, the density discontinuity at melting, and the temperature of density maximum ($T_{\mathrm{dm}}$) of the liquid. We find that the model based on MB-pol agrees well with experiment. The models based on DFT incorrectly predict that NQEs lower $T_{\mathrm{m}}$. For the density discontinuity, SCAN and SCAN0 predict values close to the experimental result, while revPBE-D3 and revPBE0-D3 significantly underestimate it. Additionally, the models based on SCAN and SCAN0 correctly predict that the $T_{\mathrm{dm}}$ is higher than $T_{\mathrm{m}}$, while those based on revPBE-D3 and revPBE0-D3 predict the opposite. We attribute the deviations of the DFT-based models from experiment to the overestimation of hydrogen bond strength. Our results set the stage for more accurate simulations of aqueous systems grounded on DFT.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23939&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23939&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ A mini-review on combinatorial solutions to the Marcus-Lushnikov irreversible aggregation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:53+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This mini-review develops a combinatorial framework for irreversible aggregation (Marcus–Lushnikov/Smoluchowski) with applications including planetesimal formation, offering potentially useful mathematical tools for modeling prebiotic/self-assembly-like clustering but not directly addressing origins-of-life chemistry or biology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.11459v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Over the past decade, a combinatorial framework for discrete, finite, and irreversibly aggregating systems has emerged. This work reviews its progress, practical applications, and limitations. We outline the approach&amp;#x27;s assumptions and foundations, based on direct enumeration of system states, contrasting with classical Smoluchowski and Marcus-Lushnikov methods. Using the constant kernel as an example, we derive combinatorial expressions for the average number of clusters of a given size and their standard deviation, and present the complete probability distribution for cluster counts. The method is then extended to several kernels (additive, product, linear-chain, condensation) by explicitly enumerating ways to form clusters of a given size. For general kernels, approximate solutions are obtained via recursive expressions, enabling predictions without explicit solutions. Applications to aerosol growth and planetesimal formation are demonstrated, with comparisons to numerical results. We summarize issues of validity and precision and propose open problems. The appendix includes partial Bell polynomials, generating functions, Lagrange inversion, potential applications, and links between combinatorial and scaling solutions of the Smoluchowski equation.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Epigenetic Control and Reprogramming-Induced Potential Landscapes of Gene Regulatory Networks: A Quantitative Theoretical Approach</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:54+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a quantitative dynamical mean-field theory extending Hopfield/spin-glass-style gene regulatory network models to include epigenetic regulation (DNA methylation and histone modifications), yielding tractable stochastic potential landscapes for stable/oscillatory cell-state dynamics relevant to development rather than direct prebiotic origins.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24427v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: We develop an extended Dynamical Mean Field Theory framework to analyze gene regulatory networks (GRNs) incorporating epigenetic modifications. Building on the Hopfield network model analogy to spin glass systems, our approach introduces dynamic terms representing DNA methylation and histone modification to capture their regulatory influence on gene expression. The resulting formulation reduces high-dimensional GRN dynamics to effective stochastic equations, enabling the characterization of both stable and oscillatory states in epigenetically regulated systems. This framework provides a tractable and quantitative method for linking gene regulatory dynamics with epigenetic control, offering new theoretical insights into developmental processes and cell fate decisions.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24427&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ A biological hydraulic accumulator: How the squirting cucumber, Ecballium elaterium, squirts its seeds</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24175"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24175</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:55+00:00</updated>
    <summary>High-speed imaging and pressure sensing reveal that the squirting cucumber stores ~1 atm of turgor-driven elastic energy in its fruit wall and releases it on detachment to eject a turbulent seed–liquid jet at up to ~30 m/s, with unexpected decoupling between stem and fruit pressure rhythms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24175v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Seed dispersal is a fundamental process that allows offspring to reach suitable habitats and colonize new environments. While most plants rely on external vectors, some have evolved mechanisms that employ the buildup of liquid pressure in a closed compartment and its explosive release to disperse their seeds. This form of energy storage, reinvented by humans for engineering applications, is termed a hydraulic accumulator. Here we investigated the fluid mechanics involved in dispersal in the squirting cucumber, Ecballium elaterium integrating high-speed videography (up to 10 000 fps), microtomography, and internal pressure sensors. We recorded long-term pressure time series showing that E. elaterium exhibits circadian (24 hour) and ultradian (short-period) rhythms. Remarkably, the measurements revealed a lack of correlation between fruit and stem turgor; while the stem showed strong circadian cycles, the fruit often did not, suggesting isolated physiological processes in different tissues. The fruit&amp;#x27;s spongy wall tissue stores elastic potential energy as turgor pressure builds to nearly one atmosphere (92-99 kPa). Upon detachment, this energy is rapidly released to expel a turbulent, particle-laden liquid jet. Microtomography revealed that the seeds are packed around a central funiculus, a configuration that optimizes their exit through the basal orifice at velocities of up to 30 m/s. Seeds eventually move faster than the liquid droplets during the later stages of ejection as they shed their liquid coating. This sophisticated mechanism ensures a broad dispersal cone, effectively spreading offspring across space and environmental conditions.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24175&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24175&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Hierarchical Loop Stabilization in Periodically Driven Elastic Networks</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:56+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Proposes an adaptation rule for periodically driven elastic transport networks showing that resonant vs anti-resonant pulsatile forcing can selectively stabilize different hierarchical loop architectures, offering a general physical mechanism for network self-organization but only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2503.19681v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Network remodeling, or adaptation, in the presence of periodically driven forcings has hereto remained largely unexplored, despite the fact that a broad class of biological transport networks, e.g. animal vasculature, depends on periodic driving (pulsatility of the heart) to maintain flow. Short-term pulsatile dynamics of compliant vessels affects the long-term structures of adapting networks; however, what the correct adaptation rule is for pulsatile flows still remains an open question. Here we propose a new adaptation rule for periodically driven complex elastic networks that accounts for the effect of short-term pulsatile dynamics on the remodeling signal at long time-scales. Using this rule to adapt hierarchical elastic networks with multiple levels of looping, we show that very different network architectures are possible at steady-state depending on the driving frequency of the pulsatile source and the geometric asymmetry of the paths between the externally driven nodes of the network. Specifically resonant frequencies are shown to prioritize the stabilization of fully looped structures or higher level loops proximal to the source, whereas anti-resonant frequencies predominantly stabilize loop-less structures or lower-level loops distal to the source. Thus, this model offers a mechanism that can explain the stabilization of phenotypically diverse loopy network architectures in response to source pulsatility under physiologically relevant conditions and in the absence of other known loop stabilization mechanisms, such as random fluctuations in the load or perfusion homogenization.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19681&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Assessment of First-Principles Methods in Modeling the Melting Properties of Water</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:57+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Systematic benchmark of first-principles and ML-driven simulations (including nuclear quantum effects) for water’s melting properties, highlighting where common DFT functionals fail and MB-pol better matches experiment—useful for habitability-relevant aqueous physics but only indirectly tied to origins-of-life chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.23940v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: First-principles simulations have played a crucial role in deepening our understanding of the thermodynamic properties of water, and machine learning potentials (MLPs) trained on these first-principles data widen the range of accessible properties. However, the capabilities of different first-principles methods are not yet fully understood due to the lack of systematic benchmarks, the underestimation of the uncertainties introduced by MLPs, and the neglect of nuclear quantum effects (NQEs). Here, we systematically assess first-principles methods by calculating key melting properties using path integral molecular dynamics (PIMD) driven by Deep Potential (DP) models trained on data from density functional theory (DFT) with SCAN, revPBE0-D3, SCAN0 and revPBE-D3 functionals, as well as from the MB-pol potential. We find that MB-pol is in qualitatively good agreement with the experiment in all properties tested, whereas the four DFT functionals incorrectly predict that NQEs increase the melting temperature. SCAN and SCAN0 slightly underestimate the density change between water and ice upon melting, but revPBE-D3 and revPBE0-D3 severely underestimate it. Moreover, SCAN and SCAN0 correctly predict that the maximum liquid density occurs at a temperature higher than the melting point, while revPBE-D3 and revPBE0-D3 predict the opposite behavior. Our results highlight limitations in widely used first-principles methods and call for a reassessment of their predictive power in aqueous systems.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23940&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Imaging nanoscale photocarrier traps in solar water-splitting catalysts</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24543"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24543</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:58+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces photomodulated STEM-EELS to directly image nanoscale photocarrier trapping at oxygen-vacancy surface defects in SrTiO3:Rh water-splitting nanoparticles, offering improved mechanistic design insight for photocatalytic water splitting.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24543v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Defects trap photocarriers and hinder solar water splitting. The nanoscale photocarrier transport, trapping, and recombination mechanisms are usually inferred from ensemble-averaged measurements and remain elusive. Because an individual high-performing nanoparticle photocatalyst may outperform the ensemble average, design rules that would otherwise enhance catalytic efficiency remain unclear. Here, we introduce photomodulated electron energy-loss spectroscopy (EELS) in an optically coupled scanning transmission electron microscope (STEM) to map photocarrier localization. Using rhodium-doped strontium titanate (SrTiO3:Rh) solar water-splitting nanoparticles, we directly image the carrier densities concentrated at oxygen-vacancy surface trap states. This is achieved by separating photothermal heating from photocarrier populations through experimental and computational analyses of low-loss spectra. Photomodulated STEM-EELS enables angstrom-scale imaging of defect-induced photocarrier traps and their impact on photocatalytic efficiency.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24543&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24543&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Thermodynamics Reconstructed from Information Theory:An Axiomatic Framework via Information-Volume Constraints and Path-Space KL Divergence</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24655"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24655</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:00:59+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents an information-theoretic axiomatic reconstruction of equilibrium and nonequilibrium thermodynamics (including entropy production and hidden dissipation) that could inform general OoL nonequilibrium frameworks but does not directly address prebiotic chemistry, protocells, or specific origin-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24655v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: We develop an axiomatic reconstruction of thermodynamics based entirely on two primitive components: a description of what aspects of a system are observed and a reference measure that encodes the underlying descriptive convention. These ingredients define an &amp;quot;information volume&amp;quot; for each observational cell. By incorporating the logarithm of this volume as an additional constraint in a minimum-relative-entropy inference scheme, temperature, chemical potential, and pressure arise as conjugate variables of a single information-theoretic functional. This leads to a Legendre-type structure and a first-law-like relation in which pressure corresponds to information volume rather than geometric volume. For nonequilibrium dynamics, entropy production is characterized through the relative-entropy asymmetry between forward and time-reversed stochastic evolutions. A decomposition using observational entropy then separates total dissipation into system and environment contributions. Heat is defined as the part of dissipation not accounted for by the system-entropy change, yielding a representation that does not rely on local detailed balance or a specific bath model. We further show that the difference between joint and partially observed dissipation equals the average of conditional relative entropies, providing a unified interpretation of hidden dissipation and information-flow terms as projection-induced gaps.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24655&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24655&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Excitons: Energetics and spatio-temporal dynamics</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.06460"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.06460</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Review overviewing modern exciton energetics and spatio-temporal dynamics in complex materials (including vibronic coupling, charge-transfer character, spin interconversion, and correlation), with only indirect relevance to Origins of Life via potential photophysical energy-transfer mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2111.06460v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: The concept of an exciton as a quasiparticle that represents collective excited states was originally adapted from solid-state physics and has been successfully applied to molecular aggregates by relying on the well-established limits of the Wannier exciton and the Frenkel exciton. However, the study of excitons in more complex chemical systems and solid materials over the past two decades has made it clear that simple concepts based on Wannier or Frenkel excitons are not sufficient to describe detailed excitonic behavior, especially in nano-structured solid materials, multichromophoric macromolecules, and complex molecular aggregates. In addition, important effects such as vibronic coupling, the influence of charge-transfer (CT) components, spin-state interconversion, and electronic correlation, which had long been studied but not fully understood, have turned out to play a central role in many systems. This has motivated new experimental approaches and theoretical studies of increasing sophistication. This article provides an overview of works addressing these issues that were published for A Special Topic of the Journal of Chemical Physics on &amp;quot;Excitons: Energetics and spatio-temporal dynamics&amp;quot; and discusses their implications.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.06460&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.06460&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Hidden long-range correlations in the ion distribution at the graphite / [bmim][NTf$_2$] electrified interface</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24900"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24900</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:01+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Molecular dynamics study of graphite–ionic liquid electrified interfaces showing long-range dipolar correlations in neutral ion pairs (modulated by charge, water uptake, temperature), offering general insight into interfacial electrochemistry that could indirectly inform prebiotic surface/gradient scenarios.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24900v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: A capacitor consisting of the [bmim][NTf$_2$] ionic liquid (IL) confined in between planar graphite electrodes has been investigated by molecular dynamics based on an all-atom, unpolarizable force field. Structural and dynamical properties such as: (i) the density and orientation of the [bmim]$^+$ and [NTf$_2$]$^-$ ions throughout the capacitor; (ii) the electrostatic double layer at the electrode / electrolyte interface; (iii) the ions&amp;#x27; mobility perpendicular and parallel to the graphite plates are determined as a function of the electrostatic charge of the capacitor, the concentration of absorbed water, the temperature and pressure. Grouping the [bmim]$^+$ and [NTf$_2$]$^-$ ions into neutral ion pairs reveals an intriguing ordering normal to the interface that is related to correlations among the dipole moments of the neutral ion pairs. These correlations might explain the observation of an anomalous Stark effect (Pockels effect) reported a few years ago in Langmuir, vol. 37, 5193-5201, (2021), and provides useful insight for the multitude of electro-chemical applications that involve electrode / ionic liquid interfaces.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24900&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24900&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Tritium accumulation and ozone decontamination of tungsten and beryllium</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24256"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24256</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:02+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Experimental study of tritium uptake on beryllium vs tungsten and shows effective decontamination requires UV-assisted ozone exposure, a result mainly relevant to fusion/materials handling rather than origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24256v1 Announce Type: cross Abstract: Tritium adsorption on surfaces creates a variety of issues, ranging from the fields of fusion applications to small and large-scale laboratory experiments using tritium. The extent to which tritium accumulates on surfaces is generally material-dependent and must be determined through experiments. Additionally, this surface contamination necessitates the implementation of appropriate decontamination procedures, preferably in-situ. A suitable method could be exposure to ozone during UV irradiation. However, it is currently not known if both components are necessary for the decontamination. At Tritium Laboratory Karlsruhe, both questions on contamination and decontamination can be addressed using a single experimental setup. With this, it is possible to expose solid samples to gaseous tritium to measure the temporal activity evolution. Furthermore, the system can be filled with dry air, and dry air containing ozone to explore their decontamination effect. Both measurement modes were applied to beryllium and tungsten samples, which were chosen for their relevance in fusion. The beryllium surface was observed to accumulate tritium more than four times faster than tungsten when exposed to gaseous tritium. Concerning the decontamination, without simultaneous UV irradiation, exposure to ozone did not have any distinct effect on the surface activity compared to simply using dry air. This leads to the conclusion that UV illumination of the surfaces is required to achieve a significant decontamination factor.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24256&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24256&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Nonadiabatic derivative couplings through multiple Franck-Condon modes dictate the energy gap law for near and short-wave infrared dye molecules</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10695"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10695</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:03+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This study elucidates a photophysical mechanism (nonadiabatic derivative couplings across multiple vibrational modes) underlying the near-universal energy gap law for fast nonradiative decay in NIR/SWIR dyes, with limited direct relevance to origins-of-life questions beyond general implications for photochemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2309.10695v3 Announce Type: replace Abstract: Near infrared (NIR, 700 - 1,000 nm) and short-wave infrared (SWIR, 1,000 - 2,000 nm) dye molecules exhibit significant nonradiative decay rates from the first singlet excited state to the ground state. While these trends can be empirically explained by a simple energy gap law, detailed mechanisms of the nearly universal behavior have remained unsettled for many cases. Theoretical and experimental results for two representative NIR/SWIR dye molecules reported here clarify the key mechanism for the observed energy gap law behavior. It is shown that the first derivative nonadiabatic coupling terms serve as major coupling pathways for nonadiabatic decay processes from the first excited singlet state to the ground state for these NIR and SWIR dye molecules and that vibrational modes other than the highest frequency ones also make significant contributions to the rate. This assessment is corroborated by further theoretical comparison with possible alternative mechanisms of intersystem crossing to triplet states and also by comparison with experimental data for deuterated molecules.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10695&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10695&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Simple and general unitarity conserving numerical real time propagators of time dependent Schr\&#34;odinger equation based on Magnus expansion</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:04+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents unitarity-preserving Magnus-expansion-based numerical propagators for time-dependent Schrödinger dynamics, a broadly useful quantum simulation method but not directly focused on origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2312.01115v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Magnus expansion (ME) provides a general way to expand the real-time propagator of a time-dependent Hamiltonian within the exponential such that the unitarity is satisfied at any order. We use this property and explicit integration of Lagrange interpolation formulas for the time-dependent Hamiltonian within each time interval and derive approximations that preserve unitarity for the differential time evolution operators of general time-dependent Hamiltonians. The resulting second-order approximation is the same as using the average of Hamiltonians for two end points of time. We identify three fourth-order approximations involving commutators of Hamiltonians at different times and also derive a sixth-order expression. A test of these approximations along with other available expressions for a two-state time-dependent Hamiltonian with sinusoidal time dependences provides information on the relative performance of these approximations and suggests that the derived expressions can serve as useful numerical tools for time evolution in time-resolved spectroscopy, quantum control, quantum sensing, real-time ab initio quantum dynamics, and open system quantum dynamics.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01115&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Enhanced premelting at the ice-rubber interface using all-atom molecular dynamics simulation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:05+00:00</updated>
    <summary>All-atom MD shows hydrophobic rubber can nonetheless enhance structural disorder and premelting at the ice interface while suppressing water mobility via polymer confinement, offering indirect astrobiology relevance for understanding liquid-like interfacial water in icy environments.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2508.20448v2 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: The ice-rubber interface is critical in applications such as tires and shoe outsoles, yet its molecular tribology remains unclear. Using all-atom molecular dynamics simulations, we studied premelting layers at the basal face of ice in contact with styrene-butadiene rubber from 254 to 269 K. Despite its hydrophobicity, rubber enhances structural disorder of interfacial water, promoting premelting. In contrast, water mobility is suppressed by confinement from polymer chains, leading to glassy dynamics distinct from the ice-vapor interface. Near the melting point, rubber chains become more flexible and penetrate the premelting layer, forming a mixed rubber-water region that couples the dynamics of both components. These results suggest that nanoscale roughness and morphology of hydrophobic polymers disrupt ice hydrogen-bond networks, thereby enhancing premelting. Our findings provide molecular-level insight into ice slipperiness and inform the design of polymer materials with controlled ice adhesion and friction.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20448&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ Martini Mapper: An Automated Fragment-Based Framework for Developing Coarse-Grained Models within the Martini 3 Framework</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:06+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents an automated SMILES-to–Martini 3 coarse-graining workflow validated on &gt;5,000 molecules (incl. octanol–water partitioning benchmarks), a broadly enabling simulation tool that could support—though does not directly address—Origins-of-Life questions involving water-mediated molecular self-assembly.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2511.11859v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: Coarse-graining (CG) reduces molecular details to extend the time and length scales of molecular dynamics simulations to microseconds and micrometers. However, the CG approaches have long been limited by the difficulty of constructing both accurate and transferable models efficiently, considering the large diversity of chemical structures of materials. Among CG force fields, Martini is the most widely used, as it retains essential chemical features while offering substantial computational efficiency. Its most recent version, Martini 3, expands chemical resolution through a much broader bead set, particularly for small molecules. However, this flexibility also complicates the mapping of organic molecules because of context-dependent rules and the lack of standardized procedures. To address this issue, we present an automated framework that builds Martini 3 models directly from SMILES (Simplified Molecular Input Line Entry System) strings by combining a curated bead dictionary with a hierarchical, rule-based algorithm. Our framework, Martini Mapper, generated Martini 3 models for more than 5,000 molecules across four chemically diverse datasets. A curated subset of 1,081 mapped structures was benchmarked through octanol-water free-energy ($\Delta G_{OW}$) and partition-coefficient ($\log P$) calculations, yielding strong agreement with experimental values. The workflow can also map large molecules containing up to 126 heavy atoms, exceeding the capabilities of existing automated approaches. The algorithm and the complete set of more than 5,000 mapped itp/top files are available at the \href{https://github.com/eliobaby/Martini_mapping}{Martini Mapper}. Our framework, therefore, enables systematic and scalable Martini 3 structures for high-throughput simulations relevant to drug discovery and materials design.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11859&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟢 Biosystems ➤ On the transitional character and regularity of planetary abiogenesis</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002709?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002709?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.280152+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This BioSystems paper appears to address origins-of-life theory by examining whether planetary abiogenesis has a transitional, regular (possibly law-like) character across worlds.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: BioSystems, Volume 259 Author(s): Serge Dolgikh
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002709?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002709?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ A mini-review on combinatorial solutions to the Marcus-Lushnikov irreversible aggregation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:01:07+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Reviews a combinatorial, state-enumeration approach to Marcus–Lushnikov irreversible aggregation (with examples like planetesimal formation), offering broadly relevant tools for self-assembly/aggregation modeling but only indirect connection to origins-of-life chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.11459v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Over the past decade, a combinatorial framework for discrete, finite, and irreversibly aggregating systems has emerged. This work reviews its progress, practical applications, and limitations. We outline the approach&amp;#x27;s assumptions and foundations, based on direct enumeration of system states, contrasting with classical Smoluchowski and Marcus-Lushnikov methods. Using the constant kernel as an example, we derive combinatorial expressions for the average number of clusters of a given size and their standard deviation, and present the complete probability distribution for cluster counts. The method is then extended to several kernels (additive, product, linear-chain, condensation) by explicitly enumerating ways to form clusters of a given size. For general kernels, approximate solutions are obtained via recursive expressions, enabling predictions without explicit solutions. Applications to aerosol growth and planetesimal formation are demonstrated, with comparisons to numerical results. We summarize issues of validity and precision and propose open problems. The appendix includes partial Bell polynomials, generating functions, Lagrange inversion, potential applications, and links between combinatorial and scaling solutions of the Smoluchowski equation.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Biosystems ➤ Prevalence of prime mass residues in single point mutations and their importance to protein stability, function and evolution</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002485?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002485?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.486890+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Analyzes how prime-mass amino acid residue patterns in single-point mutations relate to protein stability and evolutionary change, offering indirect context for molecular evolution rather than a direct origins-of-life or prebiotic chemistry focus.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: BioSystems, Volume 258 Author(s): Matthew Wright, Kevin M. Downard
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002485?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002485?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Biosystems ➤ Evolutionary computation for reconstructing threshold networks of the tryptophan operon in Escherichia coli</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002928?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002928?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.157169+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Uses evolutionary computation to reconstruct threshold gene-regulatory networks for the E. coli tryptophan operon, offering systems-biology methods with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: BioSystems, Volume 259 Author(s): Gonzalo A. Ruz, Thomas Ledger, Matthew Macauley
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002928?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002928?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Biosystems ➤ Cultural accumulation or stasis? The impact of imitation and early teaching on hominin cultural evolution</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002515?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002515?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.412334+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This BioSystems paper models how imitation and early teaching shape hominin cultural evolution, which is largely unrelated to astrobiology or chemical/biological origins-of-life research (only loosely touching on evolution in a general sense).</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: BioSystems, Volume 258 Author(s): Laureano Castro, Daniel Castro-Cañadilla, Miguel Ángel Castro-Nogueira, Miguel Ángel Toro
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002515?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002515?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Biosystems ➤ Information and the living tree of life: A theory of measurement grounded in biology</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002205?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002205?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.511605+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A conceptual/theoretical paper linking information and biological measurement to the living tree of life, offering broad evolutionary context but limited direct engagement with origins-of-life mechanisms or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: BioSystems, Volume 258 Author(s): Kevin Hudnall
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002205?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002205?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Parameter-wise predictions and sensitivity analysis for random walk models in the life sciences</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003315?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003315?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.560331+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops parameter-wise prediction and sensitivity analysis methods for random-walk models in life-science applications, with no direct connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 21 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 621 Author(s): Yihan Liu, David J. Warne, Matthew J. Simpson
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003315?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003315?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Biosystems ➤ Cooperation in structured populations via coupled reputation and learning: A spatial evolutionary game approach</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002400?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002400?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.537956+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Uses spatial evolutionary game theory to study how reputation-linked learning can sustain cooperation in structured populations, offering broad evolutionary-dynamics context but limited direct relevance to prebiotic or origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: BioSystems, Volume 258 Author(s): Shouwei Li, Bo Peng, Baochen Li, Yan Shi
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002400?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002400?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟢 Biosystems ➤ The Natural history of the transition between RNA to DNA in the early stages of life</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002813?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002813?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.381130+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A conceptual review of how early life may have transitioned from RNA-based genetics to DNA, addressing a central problem in origins-of-life research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: BioSystems, Volume 259 Author(s): Sávio Torres de Farias, Marco José
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002813?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002813?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Dynamics of integrated multi-trophic aquaculture (IMTA): A modeling approach incorporating zooplankton and scavenger</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003352?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003352?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.731989+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper models dynamics in integrated multi-trophic aquaculture involving zooplankton and scavengers, which is an applied ecological/aquaculture topic without direct relevance to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Honghui Gao, Ming Chen, Yuwei Liu
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003352?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003352?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Semi-hydraulic actuation in spider legs: The transport of the hemolymph does not hamper muscle driven leg joint flexion</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003340?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003340?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.149748+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper examines spider leg biomechanics (semi-hydraulic hemolymph transport and muscle-driven flexion) and does not address origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Reinhard Blickhan, Tobias Siebert, Tom Weihmann
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003340?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003340?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Biosystems ➤ Humans and microbes: A systems theory perspective on coevolution</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002497?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002497?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.559255+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Systems-theory discussion of human–microbe coevolution with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions (primarily via broad evolutionary framing).</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: BioSystems, Volume 258 Author(s): A.V. Melkikh
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002497?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0303264725002497?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Sucrose transport to the root and shoot in the seedling phloem</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002759?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002759?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150030+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper focuses on sucrose transport in plant seedling phloem (plant physiology) and has no evident connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Jacob M. Jepson, Leah R. Band
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002759?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002759?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Timing the initiation of sex: Delay mechanisms alter fitness outcomes in a rotifer population model</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003170?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003170?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.576744+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical population model exploring how delayed initiation of sex affects fitness in rotifers, offering indirect evolutionary context but little direct relevance to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Bethany L.F. Stevens, Silke F. van Daalen, Tirzah J. Blomquist, Kristin E. Gribble, Michael G. Neubert
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003170?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003170?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ A discrete-time continuous-space neural model for shell patterns in mollusks</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003182?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003182?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.785340+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper models mollusk shell pattern formation using a discrete-time neural framework, which is largely unrelated to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Rahnuma Islam, Bard Ermentrout, Sabrina Streipert
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003182?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003182?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Stability-driven assembly theory</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003364?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003364?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.938384+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical biology paper proposing a stability-driven framework for how complex assemblies might form, potentially relevant to origins-of-life thinking but with no explicit OoL/astrobiology details available from the provided metadata.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Dan Adler
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003364?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003364?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ A model of predation and survival in a system of three interacting species</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003145?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003145?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150170+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical ecology model of predation and survival dynamics among three interacting species, with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions beyond general evolutionary population dynamics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Anca Rǎdulescu, Richard Halpern, Drew Kozlowski
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003145?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003145?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Deciphering the modulatory role of direct pedunculopontine nucleus-cortical circuitry in absence seizure dynamics: A computational study</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003509?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003509?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150535+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Computational neuroscience study of pedunculopontine nucleus–cortical circuitry in absence seizure dynamics, with no apparent connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 29 December 2025 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology Author(s): Bing Hu, Jiaqin Peng, Wencan Li, Yuhan Xiao, Ningmin Zhu
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003509?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003509?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Modelling the spread and management of Varroa Destructor in naive European Honeybee populations</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003133?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003133?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150947+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical ecology/epidemiology modelling study on Varroa destructor management in European honeybee populations, with no direct relevance to origins-of-life or astrobiology topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 3 December 2025 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology Author(s): Isobel R. Abell, Thao P. Le, Jennifer A. Flegg, Christopher M. Baker
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003133?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003133?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Can physical activity augment drug efficacy in PMO treatments - Insights from in-silico simulations of PTH and denosumab treatments</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003376?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003376?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150816+00:00</updated>
    <summary>In-silico modeling of osteoporosis drug efficacy under physical activity (PTH and denosumab) is biomedical research with no direct connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 21 December 2025 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology Author(s): Rocío Ruiz-Lozano, José Luis Calvo-Gallego, Peter Pivonka, Javier Martínez-Reina
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003376?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003376?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Bistability in the regulatory system of the intrinsic apoptotic pathway arising from the Bax and Bcl-xL interactions</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003285?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003285?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.109551+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This theoretical modeling study of bistability in the eukaryotic intrinsic apoptotic (Bax/Bcl-xL) regulatory network is not directly relevant to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology-focused questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Ruslan M. Timchenko, Mikhail A. Panteleev
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003285?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003285?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Habitat fragmentation promotes spatial scale separation under resource competition</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003510?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003510?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150407+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical ecology study modeling how habitat fragmentation and resource competition drive spatial scale separation, with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life questions via general principles of spatial structure in evolving systems.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 30 December 2025 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology Author(s): James Austin Orgeron, Malbor Asllani
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003510?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003510?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ A mixed-effects cosinor modelling framework for circadian gene expression</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002851?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002851?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.196684+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a mixed-effects cosinor statistical framework for analyzing circadian gene expression rhythms, which is not directly relevant to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 2 November 2025 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology Author(s): Michael T. Gorczyca
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002851?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325002851?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Branch length statistics in phylogenetic trees under constant-rate birth-death dynamics</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002251932500339X?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002251932500339X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150286+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Develops statistical expectations for branch lengths in phylogenetic trees under constant-rate birth–death models, offering general evolutionary modeling tools but little direct relevance to prebiotic chemistry or origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 31 December 2025 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology Author(s): Tobias Dieselhorst, Johannes Berg
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002251932500339X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002251932500339X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Emergent stable tissue shapes from the regulatory feedback between morphogens and cell growth</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003388?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003388?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.149901+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical model showing how feedback between morphogen signaling and cell growth can produce stable tissue-scale shapes, offering broad-context insight into mechanisms that could support the emergence of organized multicellular structures but not directly addressing abiogenesis or prebiotic chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: 7 March 2026 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology, Volume 620 Author(s): Bivash Kaity, Daniel Lobo
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003388?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003388?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Theoretical Biology ➤ Spatial Sucrose Sink Profiles Shape Phloem Transport Efficiency and Xylem-Phloem Water Exchange</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003303?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003303?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.150678+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical plant-physiology study modeling how spatial sucrose sink patterns influence phloem transport and xylem–phloem water exchange, with minimal direct relevance to origins-of-life research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 24 December 2025 Source: Journal of Theoretical Biology Author(s): Mazen Nakad, Aaron Potkay, Marc A. Hesse, Maurizio Mencuccini, Pierre Gentine, Ensheng Weng
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003303?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519325003303?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Physics of Life Reviews ➤ Surfing brain waves without sinking: A commentary on “Entrainment by transcranial alternating current stimulation: Insight from models of cortical oscillations and dynamical systems theory” by M. Madadi Asl and A. Valizadeh</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001290?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001290?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.254755+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This commentary on transcranial alternating current stimulation and cortical oscillation entrainment is neuroscience-focused and does not address origins of life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, or related biosignature/habitability themes.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: Physics of Life Reviews, Volume 55 Author(s): Jeremie Lefebvre, Aref Pariz, Jean-Philippe Thivierge, Axel Hutt
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001290?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001290?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Semi-Supervised Rotation Forest</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002546?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002546?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.553609+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper on semi-supervised Rotation Forest machine learning is unrelated to origins-of-life research, astrobiology, or prebiotic chemistry and contains no relevant target-keyword signals.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): José Miguel Ramírez-Sanz, David Martínez-Acha, Álvar Arnaiz-González, César García-Osorio, Juan J. Rodríguez
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002546?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002546?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Physics of Life Reviews ➤ Making the private public: external grounding in inner States</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001563?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001563?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.148233+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper appears to address philosophical/neuroscientific issues of how internal mental states are grounded externally, with no evident connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, abiogenesis, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: Physics of Life Reviews, Volume 55 Author(s): Friedemann Pulvermüller, Michael Pauen
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001563?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001563?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Efficient utilization of streaming multiprocessors for the implementation of particle filter on graphics processing unit</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002558?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002558?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.567289+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper focuses on GPU optimization for particle filter algorithms and has no apparent connection to origins-of-life research, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignature detection.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): Özcan Dülger
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002558?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002558?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Physics of Life Reviews ➤ Remodeling of non-coding RNA regulatory networks: Decoding the pathological mechanisms and new therapeutic paradigms of cardiovascular diseases</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001836?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001836?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.015368+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A biomedical review on non-coding RNA regulatory network remodeling in cardiovascular disease, with only tangential relevance to Origins of Life via general RNA biology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: March 2026 Source: Physics of Life Reviews, Volume 56 Author(s): Wangzheqi Zhang, Lei Duan, Changli Wang, Yan Liao, Rui Zhao, Zhaoyu Li, Haoling Zhang, Zengwu Wang, Jing-jing Zhang
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001836?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001836?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Physics of Life Reviews ➤ Informational inbreeding: a useful concept to add to extant evolutionary theories: Comment on “Homo informatio” by Michael J. Walker</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001824?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001824?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.089835+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This commentary introduces the concept of “informational inbreeding” as a proposed addition to evolutionary theory, offering broad conceptual context but little direct engagement with prebiotic chemistry or core origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: March 2026 Source: Physics of Life Reviews, Volume 56 Author(s): Héctor M. Manrique, Ana Magdalena Hurtado
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001824?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001824?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Physics of Life Reviews ➤ On implementation of nonlocal terms in models in ecology and evolution. Comment on `Nonlocal models in biology and life sciences: Sources, developments, and applications&#39; by S. Pal and R. Melnic</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001897?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001897?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.092254+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical comment on how to implement nonlocal terms in ecological and evolutionary models, with little direct relevance to prebiotic chemistry, abiogenesis, or core origins-of-life questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 26 December 2025 Source: Physics of Life Reviews Author(s): Andrew Yu Morozov
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001897?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001897?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Physics of Life Reviews ➤ Modeling network connectivity may reveal further insights on how transcranial alternating current stimulation modulates brain activity: Comment on “Entrainment by transcranial alternating current stimulation: Insights from models of cortical oscillations and dynamical systems theory” by M. Madadi Asl and A. Valizadeh</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001435?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001435?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.224326+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This is a neuroscience commentary on how transcranial alternating current stimulation may modulate brain activity via network connectivity, with no apparent connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: Physics of Life Reviews, Volume 55 Author(s): Heiko I. Stecher, Daniel Strüber, Christoph S. Herrmann
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001435?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001435?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ A liquid neural network with physical evolution for variable continuous time series prediction</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002340?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002340?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.945198+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper presents a liquid neural network approach for variable continuous time-series prediction and does not address origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): Kui Qian, Yue Deng, Zhengyan Li, Xiulan Wen
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002340?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002340?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ ENOF:Outlier detection algorithm based on Elastic Neighborhood Outlier Factor</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002431?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002431?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.743082+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper presents an elastic neighborhood outlier detection algorithm (ENOF) for computational data analysis and has no apparent connection to origins-of-life research or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): Zhongping Zhang, Jinyu Dong, Kuo Wang, Zhongman Wang
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002431?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002431?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Physics of Life Reviews ➤ Simple rules for simple models</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001575?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001575?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.196336+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A theoretical review on how simple rule-based models can explain emergent biological organization, offering broad conceptual context but no explicit origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology focus from the available metadata.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: December 2025 Source: Physics of Life Reviews, Volume 55 Author(s): Arnaud Messé, Claus C. Hilgetag, Marc-Thorsten Hütt
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001575?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1571064525001575?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Algorithm for segmentation of multimodally distributed time series in accordance with their modes</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500242X?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500242X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.852764+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper presents a computational algorithm for segmenting multimodally distributed time series and does not address origins of life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): V.S. Petrakova, E.D. Karepova
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500242X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500242X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Exploring network-level indicators for project analysis — A comparison of real and synthetic projects</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002224?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002224?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.120509+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper compares network-level indicators for analyzing real versus synthetic project structures in computational science, with no apparent connection to origins-of-life, astrobiology, or prebiotic chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Zsolt T. Kosztyán
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002224?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002224?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Enhancing urban solar photovoltaic system performance evaluation through a disc spherical fuzzy aggregation framework</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002352?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002352?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.091049+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops a disc spherical fuzzy aggregation framework to evaluate urban solar photovoltaic system performance, with no apparent connection to origins of life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignature detection.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Shahzaib Ashraf, Muhammad Shakir Chohan, Wania Iqbal, Vladimir Simic, Dragan Pamucar, Nebojsa Bacanin
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002352?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002352?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ A local–global Graph Transformer model for fluid dynamics simulations</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002509?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002509?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.707719+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper presents a graph transformer approach for fluid dynamics simulation and does not address origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, habitability, or astrobiological biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): Jiamin Jiang, Jingrun Chen, Zhouwang Yang
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002509?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002509?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ MOOSE ProbML: Parallelized probabilistic machine learning and uncertainty quantification for computational energy applications</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002534?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002534?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.560039+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Describes a parallelized probabilistic machine-learning and uncertainty-quantification framework for computational energy applications, with no direct connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): Somayajulu L.N. Dhulipala, Peter German, Yifeng Che, Zachary M. Prince, Xianjian Xie, Pierre-Clément A. Simon, Vincent M. Labouré, Hao Yan
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002534?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002534?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Computational modeling of incompressible two-phase fluid dynamics via the conservative Allen–Cahn framework on a virtual cube</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002327?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002327?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.036389+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops a conservative Allen–Cahn computational framework for incompressible two-phase fluid dynamics on a virtual cube and does not address origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Ahmed Zeeshan, Juho Ma, Zhengang Li, Xinpei Wu, Junseok Kim
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002327?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002327?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ A novel deep transfer learning model with a bidirectional quasi-recurrent neural network for underwater object classification from aquarium images</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002522?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002522?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:42.614234+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper presents a deep transfer learning approach (bidirectional quasi-recurrent neural network) for classifying underwater objects in aquarium images, with only a tangential connection to astrobiology via the generic keyword &#34;water&#34;.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: February 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 94 Author(s): Tabeer Jan, Lavanya Madhuri Bollipo
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002522?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002522?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Two improved physics-informed Neural Networks for solving Burgers equation</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002339?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002339?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.158455+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops improved physics-informed neural networks for solving the Burgers equation, a computational mathematics topic with no evident connection to origins-of-life, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Zeyue Zhang, Chunlei Ruan, Zhijun Liu
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002339?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002339?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Safe merging aircraft flows in multi-route schemes</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002182?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002182?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.269694+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Computational modeling of safe merging of aircraft traffic flows in multi-route schemes, with no apparent connection to origins of life, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Arseniy A. Spiridonov
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002182?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002182?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Thought Management System for long-horizon, goal-driven LLM agents</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002170?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002170?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.229869+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper focuses on long-horizon, goal-driven large language model agent architecture and contains no apparent relevance to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, or biosignature/habitability research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Andrii Bidochko, Yaroslav Vyklyuk
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002170?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002170?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Local method of fundamental solutions formulations for polyharmonic BVPs</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002194?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002194?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.286998+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops numerical formulations (local method of fundamental solutions) for solving polyharmonic boundary value problems and has no apparent connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, habitability, or biosignature detection.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Andreas Karageorghis, C.S. Chen, Malgorzata A. Jankowska
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002194?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002194?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ ELM-UNet: An efficient and lightweight Vision Mamba UNet for skin lesion segmentation</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002200?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002200?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.308719+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper presents a lightweight Vision Mamba UNet architecture for medical image (skin lesion) segmentation and has no apparent connection to origins of life, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignature research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Songling Xia, Hongwei Deng, Feng Chen
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002200?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002200?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ A generalized colouring method for a parallelizable integer linear programming approach to polyomino tiling</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500211X?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500211X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.620303+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops a computational method for parallelizable integer linear programming in polyomino tiling and has no apparent connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Marcus R. Garvie, John Burkardt
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500211X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500211X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ A Novel Exact Solution of Extended Single Particle Model for Lithium-ion Cell and Its Application to High Capacity NMC Battery</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002571?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002571?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.893345+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Computational electrochemistry paper presenting an exact solution for an extended single-particle lithium-ion battery model, with no evident connection to astrobiology or origins-of-life research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 31 December 2025 Source: Journal of Computational Science Author(s): Arif Ullah Khan, Mahvish Samar, Arif Hussain, Mei Li, Wenting Xu, Zhiyu Mao, Zhongwei Chen
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002571?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002571?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Fuzzy data imputation with DIMP and FGAIN</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002157?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002157?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.396023+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper develops fuzzy methods for missing-data imputation (DIMP and FGAIN) in computational science and does not address origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Maciej Romaniuk, Przemysław Grzegorzewski
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002157?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002157?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Computational model of ammonia synthesis with catalyst pellets: Linking the structure and performance</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002145?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002145?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.437052+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A computational chemical engineering study modeling catalyst pellet structure–performance relationships in industrial ammonia synthesis, with minimal direct relevance to origins-of-life or astrobiology themes.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Michael Abeiku Daniels, Anna Geohagan, Agnieszka Truszkowska
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002145?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002145?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Efficient cellular automata-Lattice Boltzmann method for modeling solidification microstructure</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002121?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002121?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.643513+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Computational materials-science method paper on modeling solidification microstructures (cellular automata–lattice Boltzmann), with no clear connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Jingjing Wang, Xiaoyu Liu, Ruina Mao
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002121?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002121?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ A nonlinear finite volume scheme preserving positivity for the numerical simulation of groundwater contaminant transport in porous media</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002169?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002169?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.437268+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Presents a positivity-preserving nonlinear finite volume numerical scheme for simulating contaminant transport in groundwater (water-related but not directly relevant to origins-of-life or astrobiology).</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Sadiq Hamidi, Mustapha El Ossmani, Abdelaziz Taakili
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002169?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002169?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Temporal carbon neutral Chinese knowledge graph completion method based on latent semantic mining</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002212?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002212?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.893149+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Computational method for temporal carbon-neutral Chinese knowledge graph completion via latent semantic mining, with no apparent connection to origins-of-life, astrobiology, or biosignature/habitability research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 31 December 2025 Source: Journal of Computational Science Author(s): Xiping Zhu, Lijuan Xiao, Ang Gao, Lu Guo, Huan Yang
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002212?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002212?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Parallel sparsity patterns for factored incomplete inverse matrices</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002133?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002133?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.554976+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper focuses on numerical methods for parallel sparse matrix computations (factored incomplete inverse matrices) and has no apparent connection to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiology topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s): Christos K. Filelis-Papadopoulos, George A. Gravvanis
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002133?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002133?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Editorial Board</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500239X?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500239X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.822081+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This appears to be an editorial-board listing with no scientific content or relevance to origins-of-life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: January 2026 Source: Journal of Computational Science, Volume 93 Author(s):
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500239X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187775032500239X?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ DEVELOPMENT AND IMPLEMENTATION OF A TOOL FOR THE ANALYSIS AND CIRCUIT REPRESENTATION OF STEADY-STATE ALTERNATING CURRENT CIRCUITS</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002510?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002510?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.893480+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper describes a computational tool for analyzing and representing steady-state alternating current circuits, with no apparent connection to origins of life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 25 December 2025 Source: Journal of Computational Science Author(s): Celal Atalar, Selda Bayrak, Huseyin Pehlivan
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002510?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002510?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Corrigendum to “Towards universal MPI bindings for enhanced new language support” [J. Comput. Sci. 87 (2025), 102557]</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325001516?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325001516?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.893641+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Corrigendum concerning universal MPI bindings for programming language support, with no apparent connection to origins of life, astrobiology, habitability, or biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 22 October 2025 Source: Journal of Computational Science Author(s): César Piñeiro, Álvaro Vázquez, Juan C. Pichel
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325001516?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325001516?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Sciences et Avenir ➤ Dans les ruines des mondes virtuels</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/high-tech/web/dans-les-ruines-des-mondes-virtuels_190135?xtor=RSS-12"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/high-tech/web/dans-les-ruines-des-mondes-virtuels_190135?xtor=RSS-12</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T07:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper discusses the digital archaeology of abandoned virtual worlds (e.g., Second Life) and does not address origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, habitability, or astrobiological biosignatures.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Utopies peuplées d&amp;#x27;avatars, les univers virtuels tel Second Life ont fleuri au tournant du 21e siècle. Leur disparition a laissé des vestiges numériques qui font l&amp;#x27;objet de fouilles minutieuses.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/high-tech/web/dans-les-ruines-des-mondes-virtuels_190135?xtor=RSS-12&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Sciences et Avenir ➤ La Réunion: éruption &#34;probable ou imminente&#34; du Piton de la Fournaise</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/nature-environnement/la-reunion-eruption-probable-ou-imminente-du-piton-de-la-fournaise_190243?xtor=RSS-15"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/nature-environnement/la-reunion-eruption-probable-ou-imminente-du-piton-de-la-fournaise_190243?xtor=RSS-15</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:03:04+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Brief news update on seismic unrest and likely imminent eruption at Piton de la Fournaise, with only indirect relevance to origins-of-life via general volcanic/geochemical context.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    La Préfecture de La Réunion a annoncé tôt jeudi le passage en alerte 1 du volcan du Piton de la fournaise pour &amp;quot;éruption probable ou imminente&amp;quot; et fermé l&amp;#x27;accès. &amp;quot;Depuis 4h47 (1h47 à Paris, NDLR), l&amp;#x27;Observatoire du Piton de la Fournaise relève une crise sismique au volcan&amp;quot;, a indiqué la préfecture sur son compte X. &amp;quot;Ceci indique que le magma est en train de quitter le réservoir magmatique et se propage vers la surface&amp;quot;, précise l&amp;#x27;observatoire dans un communiqué jeudi.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/nature-environnement/la-reunion-eruption-probable-ou-imminente-du-piton-de-la-fournaise_190243?xtor=RSS-15&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Journal of Computational Science ➤ Artificial intelligence and high-performance computing for advanced simulations</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002078?dgcid=rss_sd_all"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002078?dgcid=rss_sd_all</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T19:51:43.893790+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper discusses AI and high-performance computing approaches for advanced simulations in computational science but does not specifically address origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or astrobiological applications.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Publication date: Available online 8 October 2025 Source: Journal of Computational Science Author(s): Maciej Paszyński, David Pardo, Barbara Strug
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002078?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877750325002078?dgcid=rss_sd_all&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟡 Sciences et Avenir ➤ Luca, l&#39;ancêtre de tous les êtres vivants</title>
    <link href="https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/archeo-paleo/evolution/luca-l-ancetre-de-tous-les-etres-vivants_190060?xtor=RSS-4"/>
    <id>https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/archeo-paleo/evolution/luca-l-ancetre-de-tous-les-etres-vivants_190060?xtor=RSS-4</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Article de synthèse sur LUCA (dernier ancêtre commun universel) visant à préciser l’origine et les caractéristiques de l’ancêtre commun aux bactéries, archées et eucaryotes, pertinent pour le contexte des origines de la vie mais sans données académiques primaires ni lien DOI.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Les scientifiques recherchent l&amp;#x27;origine et les caractéristiques de cet organisme commun aux bactéries, aux archées et aux eucaryotes.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencesetavenir.fr/archeo-paleo/evolution/luca-l-ancetre-de-tous-les-etres-vivants_190060?xtor=RSS-4&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>