<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Astrobiology AI Digest - KEYWORDS-ASTROBIOLOGY</title>
  <subtitle>Hourly AI-curated papers on Origins of Life</subtitle>
  <link href="https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/keywords-astrobiology.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://github.com/champagnealexandre/ooldigest"/>
  <updated>2026-01-01T13:39:37.680975+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/keywords-astrobiology.xml</id>
  <author><name>AI Agent</name></author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 The New York Times ➤ Space Events 2026: NASA’s Artemis II Moon Mission, Summer Eclipse and More</title>
    <link href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/30/science/space-nasa-spacex-blue-origin-astronomy.html"/>
    <id>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/30/science/space-nasa-spacex-blue-origin-astronomy.html</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T11:03:48+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A general-interest roundup of 2026 space events (including Artemis II and Mars-related missions) with little direct relevance to origins-of-life, prebiotic chemistry, or biosignature/habitability research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    In 2026, there will be journeys to the moon and Mars, new visions of the cosmos and a solar eclipse that might be worth traveling for.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/30/science/space-nasa-spacex-blue-origin-astronomy.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org ➤ Seafloor Weathering and Stochastic Outgassing Unlikely to Significantly Shorten the Future Lifespan of Earth&#39;s Terrestrial Biosphere</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:58:59+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Modeling suggests seafloor weathering and unusually large stochastic CO2 outgassing variations could modestly shorten—but likely not below ~1 Gyr—the remaining lifespan of Earth’s terrestrial biosphere, supporting robustness of long-term planetary habitability estimates relevant to exoplanets.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.24538v1 Announce Type: new Abstract: Current understanding suggests that as the Sun brightens in the far future, Earth&amp;#x27;s carbonate-silicate cycle will offset increasing temperatures by drawing CO$_2$ out of the atmosphere, ultimately leading to the extinction of all terrestrial plant life via either overheating or CO$_2$ starvation. Most previous estimates put the future lifespan of Earth&amp;#x27;s terrestrial biosphere at $\sim$1 billion yr, but recent work used a new coupled climate-continental weathering model with up-to-date parameter constraints to revise this estimate upward to 1.6-1.86 billion yr. In this study, we extend the model to examine the impacts of seafloor weathering and stochastic variations in CO$_2$ outgassing rates on the remaining lifespan of Earth&amp;#x27;s terrestrial biosphere. We find that if seafloor weathering has a stronger feedback than continental weathering and accounts for a large portion of global silicate weathering, then the remaining lifespan of the terrestrial biosphere can be shortened, but a lifespan of more than 1 billion yr (Gyr) remains likely. Similarly, stochastic fluctuations in outgassing rates can have a significant impact if the size of the fluctuations exceed those observed over the last 1 billion yr. The impact of weak seafloor weathering and lower variability stochasticity are minor. Our work provisionally supports a lengthened lifespan of Earth&amp;#x27;s terrestrial biosphere, suggests robustness of this lengthened lifespan to planetary parameters that may vary among exoplanets, and identifies seafloor weathering as a key process that requires further study and constraint.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24538&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org ➤ EMPEROR I. Exoplanet MCMC parallel tempering for RV orbit retrieval</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:59:00+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces an open-source RV inference framework (dynamic nested sampling + adaptive parallel tempering with flexible stellar-noise models) that can improve recovery of low-mass exoplanet signals, but it is primarily methodological and not directly focused on habitability, biosignatures, or origins-of-life processes.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2511.05331v2 Announce Type: replace Abstract: We present EMPEROR, an open-source Python framework designed for efficient exoplanet detection and characterisation with radial velocities (RV). EMPEROR integrates Dynamic Nested Sampling (DNS) and Adaptive Parallel Tempering (APT) Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), supporting multiple noise models such as Gaussian Processes (GPs) and Moving Averages (MA). The framework enables systematic model comparison using statistical metrics, including Bayesian evidence ($\ln{\mathcal{Z}}$) and Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC), while providing automated, publish-ready visualisations. EMPEROR is evaluated across three distinct systems to assess its capabilities in different detection scenarios. Sampling performance, model selection, and the search for Earth-mass planets are evaluated in data for 51 Pegasi, HD 55693 and Barnard&amp;#x27;s Star (GJ 699). For 51 Pegasi, APT achieves an effective sampling increase over DNS by a factor 3.76, while retrieving tighter parameter estimates. For HD 55693 the stellar rotation $P_{\text{rot}}=29.72^{+0.01}_{-0.02}$ and magnetic cycle $P_{\text{mag}}=2557.0^{+70.1}_{-36.7}$ are recovered, while demonstrating the sensitivity of $\ln{\mathcal{Z}}$ to prior selection. For Barnard&amp;#x27;s star, several noise models are compared, and the confirmed planet parameters are successfully retrieved with all of them. The best model shows a period of 3.1536$\pm$0.0003~d, minimum mass of 0.38$\pm$0.03 M$_{\rm{\oplus}}$, and semi-major axis of 0.02315$\pm$0.00039~AU. Purely statistical inference might be insufficient on its own for robust exoplanet detection. Effective methodologies must integrate domain knowledge, heuristic criteria, and multi-faceted model comparisons. The versatility of EMPEROR in handling diverse noise structures, its systematic model selection, and its improved performance make it a valuable tool for RV exoplanetary studies.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05331&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 math-ph updates on arXiv.org ➤ A mini-review on combinatorial solutions to the Marcus-Lushnikov irreversible aggregation</title>
    <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459"/>
    <id>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459</id>
    <updated>2026-01-01T05:07:50+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Mini-review of combinatorial, state-enumeration methods for irreversible aggregation (Marcus–Lushnikov/Smoluchowski) with example kernels and applications including aerosol growth and planetesimal formation, offering tools potentially relevant to prebiotic self-assembly modeling but not explicitly focused on origins-of-life chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    arXiv:2512.11459v3 Announce Type: replace-cross Abstract: Over the past decade, a combinatorial framework for discrete, finite, and irreversibly aggregating systems has emerged. This work reviews its progress, practical applications, and limitations. We outline the approach&amp;#x27;s assumptions and foundations, based on direct enumeration of system states, contrasting with classical Smoluchowski and Marcus-Lushnikov methods. Using the constant kernel as an example, we derive combinatorial expressions for the average number of clusters of a given size and their standard deviation, and present the complete probability distribution for cluster counts. The method is then extended to several kernels (additive, product, linear-chain, condensation) by explicitly enumerating ways to form clusters of a given size. For general kernels, approximate solutions are obtained via recursive expressions, enabling predictions without explicit solutions. Applications to aerosol growth and planetesimal formation are demonstrated, with comparisons to numerical results. We summarize issues of validity and precision and propose open problems. The appendix includes partial Bell polynomials, generating functions, Lagrange inversion, potential applications, and links between combinatorial and scaling solutions of the Smoluchowski equation.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11459&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Radio-Canada ➤ Carambolage majeur impliquant une trentaine de véhicules dans Lotbinière</title>
    <link href="https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2217121/carambolages-lotbiniere-accident-chaudiere-appalaches"/>
    <id>https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2217121/carambolages-lotbiniere-accident-chaudiere-appalaches</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T21:34:02+00:00</updated>
    <summary>News report about a major multi-vehicle highway collision and road closure in Lotbinière, with no connection to origins-of-life or astrobiology research.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Les multiples collisions ont forcé la fermeture d&amp;#x27;un segment de l&amp;#x27;autoroute 20 Ouest.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2217121/carambolages-lotbiniere-accident-chaudiere-appalaches&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Radio-Canada ➤ Carambolage impliquant une quinzaine de véhicules dans Lotbinière</title>
    <link href="https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2217121/carambolages-lotbiniere-accident-chaudiere-appalaches"/>
    <id>https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2217121/carambolages-lotbiniere-accident-chaudiere-appalaches</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T21:34:03+00:00</updated>
    <summary>News report about a multi-vehicle traffic accident closing a section of Autoroute 20 Ouest, with no relevance to origins of life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Les collisions forcent la fermeture d&amp;#x27;un segment de l&amp;#x27;autoroute 20 Ouest.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2217121/carambolages-lotbiniere-accident-chaudiere-appalaches&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Astrobiology ➤ Hubble Reveals The Largest Chaotic Birthplace of Planets Yet Discovered</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/hubble-reveals-the-largest-chaotic-birthplace-of-planets-yet-discovered.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/hubble-reveals-the-largest-chaotic-birthplace-of-planets-yet-discovered.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T19:34:41+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Hubble imaging of an unusually large, turbulent protoplanetary disk provides broad astrobiology-relevant context on planet-forming environments but offers no direct insight into prebiotic chemistry or abiogenesis.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Astronomers using NASA’s Hubble Space Telescope have imaged the largest protoplanetary disk ever observed circling a young star. For the first time in visible light, Hubble has revealed the disk is unexpectedly chaotic and turbulent, with wisps of material stretching much farther above and belowthe disk than astronomers have seen in any similar system. Strangely, […] The post Hubble Reveals The Largest Chaotic Birthplace of Planets Yet Discovered appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3847/1538-4357/ae247f&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.3847/1538-4357/ae247f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae247f&#34;&gt;[Full Paper] https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae247f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/hubble-reveals-the-largest-chaotic-birthplace-of-planets-yet-discovered.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ Breakthrough Listen Observations Of 3I/ATLAS With The Green Bank Telescope at 1-12 GHz</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/breakthrough-listen-observations-of-3i-atlas-with-the-green-bank-telescope-at-1-12-ghz.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/breakthrough-listen-observations-of-3i-atlas-with-the-green-bank-telescope-at-1-12-ghz.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T19:34:42+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Reports Breakthrough Listen Green Bank Telescope 1–12 GHz radio observations of interstellar comet 3I/ATLAS (primarily relevant to SETI/astrobiology context rather than directly to prebiotic chemistry or origins-of-life mechanisms).</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    3I/ATLAS (also designated C/2025 N1 (ATLAS) and, formerly, A11pl3Z) is the third interstellar object (ISO), following 1I/‘Oumuamua and 2I/Borisov, to be discovered during a passage through the Solar System. The Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System (ATLAS) reported its discovery on 2025 July 1 (S. Deen et al. 2025). Unlike 1I/‘Oumuamua, 3I/ATLAS exhibits mostly typical cometary […] The post Breakthrough Listen Observations Of 3I/ATLAS With The Green Bank Telescope at 1-12 GHz appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19763&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19763&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.19763&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.19763&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/breakthrough-listen-observations-of-3i-atlas-with-the-green-bank-telescope-at-1-12-ghz.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟡 Astrobiology ➤ The Deepest Gas Hydrate Cold Seep Ever Discovered In The Arctic</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-deepest-gas-hydrate-cold-seep-ever-discovered-in-the-arctic.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-deepest-gas-hydrate-cold-seep-ever-discovered-in-the-arctic.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T19:34:43+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A Nature Communications study reports the deepest known Arctic gas-hydrate cold seep and its thriving deep-sea ecosystem, providing an extreme-environment analog relevant to astrobiology and potential origin-of-life habitats but not directly addressing prebiotic chemistry or abiogenesis.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    A multinational scientific team led by UiT has uncovered the deepest known gas hydrate cold seep on the planet. The discovery was made during the Ocean Census Arctic Deep – EXTREME24 expedition and reveals a previously unknown ecosystem thriving at 3,640 metres on the Molloy Ridge in the Greenland Sea. The groundbreaking findings regarding the Freya Hydrate […] The post The Deepest Gas Hydrate Cold Seep Ever Discovered In The Arctic appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-025-67165-x&#34;&gt;[Full Paper] https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-025-67165-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-deepest-gas-hydrate-cold-seep-ever-discovered-in-the-arctic.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Astrobiology ➤ Tricorder Tech: Space AI: Leveraging Artificial Intelligence for Space to Improve Life on Earth</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/tricorder-tech-space-ai-leveraging-artificial-intelligence-for-space-to-improve-life-on-earth.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/tricorder-tech-space-ai-leveraging-artificial-intelligence-for-space-to-improve-life-on-earth.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T19:34:44+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A position-style overview arguing for “Space AI” as an interdisciplinary field enabling autonomous space operations with potential downstream benefits for Earth, but it contains little direct content on origins-of-life mechanisms or prebiotic chemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Artificial Intelligence (AI) is transforming domains from healthcare and agriculture to finance and industry. As progress on Earth meets growing constraints, the next frontier is outer space, where AI can enable autonomous, resilient operations under extreme uncertainty and limited human oversight. This paper introduces Space AI as a unified interdisciplinary field at the intersection of […] The post Tricorder Tech: Space AI: Leveraging Artificial Intelligence for Space to Improve Life on Earth appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22399&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22399&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.22399&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.22399&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/tricorder-tech-space-ai-leveraging-artificial-intelligence-for-space-to-improve-life-on-earth.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Manchettes ➤ 2025, l’année du basculement de l’ordre mondial</title>
    <link href="https://www.ledevoir.com/monde/944829/2025-annee-basculement-ordre-mondial"/>
    <id>https://www.ledevoir.com/monde/944829/2025-annee-basculement-ordre-mondial</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T17:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <summary>French geopolitics commentary on shifts in global power after Donald Trump’s return, with no connection to origins-of-life, astrobiology, or related prebiotic chemistry topics.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Le retour au pouvoir de Donald Trump a rebrassé les cartes des rapports de force sur la planète.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ledevoir.com/monde/944829/2025-annee-basculement-ordre-mondial&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 LaPresse.ca ➤ Les nouveaux milliardaires de l’IA</title>
    <link href="https://www.lapresse.ca/affaires/techno/2025-12-30/les-nouveaux-milliardaires-de-l-ia.php?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=fil&amp;utm_campaign=affaires&amp;utm_content=techno"/>
    <id>https://www.lapresse.ca/affaires/techno/2025-12-30/les-nouveaux-milliardaires-de-l-ia.php?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=fil&amp;utm_campaign=affaires&amp;utm_content=techno</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T17:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <summary>News-style piece on AI-driven wealth gains (Nvidia/OpenAI) with no apparent connection to origins-of-life research, prebiotic chemistry, astrobiology, or habitability.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Le boom de l’intelligence artificielle (IA) a transformé des milliardaires de haut profil comme Jensen Huang, PDG du fabricant de puces Nvidia, et Sam Altman, PDG d’OpenAI, créateur de ChatGPT, en milliardaires encore plus riches.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lapresse.ca/affaires/techno/2025-12-30/les-nouveaux-milliardaires-de-l-ia.php?utm_source=rss&amp;amp;utm_medium=fil&amp;amp;utm_campaign=affaires&amp;amp;utm_content=techno&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Astrobiology ➤ Precise Physical Parameters, Habitability, and Orbital Stability of Sun-like SB2 Systems: HD 130669, HD 184467, HD 191854, and HD 214222</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/precise-physical-parameters-habitability-and-orbital-stability-of-sun-like-sb2-systems-hd-130669-hd-184467-hd-191854-and-hd-214222-2.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/precise-physical-parameters-habitability-and-orbital-stability-of-sun-like-sb2-systems-hd-130669-hd-184467-hd-191854-and-hd-214222-2.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T18:35:01+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Determines precise stellar and orbital parameters for four Sun-like SB2 binaries and uses them to assess habitable-zone placement and orbital stability, providing contextual constraints on where potentially habitable planets could persist but offering limited direct insight into origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    This work analyzes four Sun-like double-lined spectroscopic binary (SB2) systems by combining visual and spectroscopic observational data with Al-Wardat’s atmospheric modeling method to accurately determine their fundamental parameters. For each system, we determine stellar masses, orbital parallaxes, effective temperatures, spectral types, semimajor axes, and eccentricities with high precision, resolving discrepancies between astrometric and spectroscopic measurements. […] The post Precise Physical Parameters, Habitability, and Orbital Stability of Sun-like SB2 Systems: HD 130669, HD 184467, HD 191854, and HD 214222 appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23652&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23652&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3847/1538-3881/ae0582&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.3847/1538-3881/ae0582&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.23652&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.23652&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/precise-physical-parameters-habitability-and-orbital-stability-of-sun-like-sb2-systems-hd-130669-hd-184467-hd-191854-and-hd-214222-2.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟡 ChemRxiv ➤ Assessing cell survival and biosignature preservation of the extremely thermoacidophilic archaeon Acidianus manzaensis after exposure to Mars-like conditions</title>
    <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-xc7vd-v4?rft_dat=source%3Ddrss"/>
    <id>https://dx.doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-xc7vd-v4?rft_dat=source%3Ddrss</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T17:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Mars-simulation experiments show the thermoacidophilic archaeon Acidianus manzaensis can be re-cultivated after desiccation and Mars-like exposure, while its thiophene-bearing quinone profile is evaluated as a potential preservable biosignature relevant to Mars life-detection efforts.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Considering the harsh surface conditions on Mars, terrestrial organisms that can survive and remain detectable after exposure to similar conditions provide invaluable models for guiding current and future search-for-life missions. To this end, we evaluated the extremophilic archaeon Acidianus manzaensis grown on ESA01-E Mars analog material as a model organism. We exposed cell-mineral mixtures to one month of desiccation and two weeks of Mars-like conditions in a Mars simulation chamber to evaluate the potential for cell survival after exposure to these conditions. In the search for reliable biomarkers in other planetary environments, such as Mars, molecules that are stable over geological timescales while preserving information indicative of their potential biological origin are crucial. Thiophene-bearing quinones fulfill these requirements, and thiophenes, which are their basic moieties, have been discovered on Mars. Therefore, we analyzed the thiophene-bearing quinone composition of A. manzaensis using mass spectrometry-based metabolomics and discussed potential molecular alterations. Successful re-cultivation after one month of desiccation and two weeks of exposure to Mars-like conditions proved the durability of the organism and its capability for cell recovery after exposure to extreme conditions, paving the way for further investigation.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://dx.doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-xc7vd-v4?rft_dat=source%3Ddrss&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://dx.doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-xc7vd-v4?rft_dat=source%3Ddrss&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Nature Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution Community ➤ Net-Zero Objectives and Food Security under Climate Change</title>
    <link href="https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change"/>
    <id>https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T17:41:15+00:00</updated>
    <summary>An editorial-style summary on how net-zero climate policies intersect with food security under climate change, with only indirect relevance to astrobiology via general planetary habitability context rather than origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    This summary was written by Hamed Kioumarsi, an editorial board member at Springer Nature, in collaboration with Marzieh Alidoust Pahmedani, an agricultural researcher and author, and Abhijit Sagar, a global sustainability and media expert.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Nature Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution Community ➤ Net-Zero Objectives and Food Security under Climate Change: Progress, Trade-Offs, and Pathways toward the Sustainable Development Goals</title>
    <link href="https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change-progress-trade-offs-and-pathways-toward-the-sustainable-development-goals"/>
    <id>https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change-progress-trade-offs-and-pathways-toward-the-sustainable-development-goals</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T17:41:16+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A sustainability-focused review discussing how net-zero climate policies interact with food security and SDG pathways, offering minimal direct relevance to origins-of-life or prebiotic/astrobiological questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    This summary was written by Hamed Kioumarsi, an editorial board member at Springer Nature, in collaboration with Marzieh Alidoust Pahmedani, an agricultural researcher and author, and Abhijit Sagar, a global media leader.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change-progress-trade-offs-and-pathways-toward-the-sustainable-development-goals&#39;&gt;Direct Journal Link (Original Article)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://communities.springernature.com/posts/net-zero-objectives-and-food-security-under-climate-change-progress-trade-offs-and-pathways-toward-the-sustainable-development-goals&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Astrobiology ➤ Not Just Gas: How Solid-Driven Torques Shaped the Migration of the Galilean Moons</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/not-just-gas-how-solid-driven-torques-shaped-the-migration-of-the-galilean-moons.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/not-just-gas-how-solid-driven-torques-shaped-the-migration-of-the-galilean-moons.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-31T18:35:02+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Two-fluid FARGO3D simulations show that including solids in circumjovian disk models can significantly modify migration torques on proto-Galilean moons, influencing their final orbits and thus the broader context for Jovian moon habitability.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    The primary aim of this study is to investigate the orbital migration of the Galilean moons by incorporating self-consistent solid dynamics in circumjovian disk models. We perform two-fluid simulations using the FARGO3D code on a 2D polar grid. The simulations model a satellite with the mass of a proto-moon, Europa, or Ganymede interacting with a […] The post Not Just Gas: How Solid-Driven Torques Shaped the Migration of the Galilean Moons appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23542&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23542&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.23542&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2512.23542&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/not-just-gas-how-solid-driven-torques-shaped-the-migration-of-the-galilean-moons.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Radio-Canada ➤ Les recherches reprennent pour retrouver le vol MH370, 11 ans après sa disparition</title>
    <link href="https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2216896/disparition-vol-mh370-malaysia-airlines"/>
    <id>https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2216896/disparition-vol-mh370-malaysia-airlines</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T22:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <summary>News update on renewed search efforts for Malaysia Airlines flight MH370, with no connection to origins of life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    L&amp;#x27;avion a disparu des radars le 8 mars 2014 alors qu’il effectuait la liaison entre Kuala Lumpur et Pékin.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2216896/disparition-vol-mh370-malaysia-airlines&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Astrobiology ➤ LIFE NASA RCN Seminar 6 January 2026</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/life-nasa-rcn-seminar-6-january-2026.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/life-nasa-rcn-seminar-6-january-2026.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T19:35:02+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Seminar announcement highlighting work on deconvolving ancient biomarker signals to infer early ecosystem (eukaryotic) composition, relevant to interpreting biosignatures but not a primary origins-of-life study.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Join the 2026 LIFE NASA RCN Seminar Series! This month’s speakers are Dr. Ilya Bobrovskiy and Dr. Tharika Liyanage. Time: January 6th, 8AM PDT/11AM EDTJOIN Title: Unmixing ancient biomarker signals to recover primary ecosystem composition. Dr. Ilya Bobrovskiy leads a research group at MARUM that seeks to deconvolve the early record of eukaryotic evolution using […] The post LIFE NASA RCN Seminar 6 January 2026 appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/life-nasa-rcn-seminar-6-january-2026.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ Redox Diversity of Interstellar Compounds and Human Nutrients Reveals a Potentially Universal Chemical Constraint for Life</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/redox-diversity-of-interstellar-compounds-and-human-nutrients-reveals-a-potentially-universal-chemical-constraint-for-life.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/redox-diversity-of-interstellar-compounds-and-human-nutrients-reveals-a-potentially-universal-chemical-constraint-for-life.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T19:35:03+00:00</updated>
    <summary>The paper compares redox classifications across interstellar molecules, human nutrients, and PubChem to argue for a potentially universal redox-balance constraint that could shape life’s chemistry, offering broad (but not direct mechanistic) relevance to origins-of-life and astrochemical preselection.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Comparative analysis of redox properties across three chemically distinct datasets—interstellar compounds, human nutritional molecules, and &amp;gt;40 million substances in the PubChem database—reveals a striking and highly non-random pattern. Interstellar molecules and human nutrients exhibit nearly identical proportions of prooxidant, proreductant, and amphoteric species. In contrast, the PubChem chemical space is overwhelmingly dominated by amphoteric molecules […] The post Redox Diversity of Interstellar Compounds and Human Nutrients Reveals a Potentially Universal Chemical Constraint for Life appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/&#34;&gt;[PubMed/NCBI] https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/redox-diversity-of-interstellar-compounds-and-human-nutrients-reveals-a-potentially-universal-chemical-constraint-for-life.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 New Scientist ➤ Star that seemed to vanish more than 130 years ago is found again</title>
    <link href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2509810-star-that-seemed-to-vanish-more-than-130-years-ago-is-found-again/?utm_campaign=RSS%7CNSNS&amp;utm_source=NSNS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_content=home"/>
    <id>https://www.newscientist.com/article/2509810-star-that-seemed-to-vanish-more-than-130-years-ago-is-found-again/?utm_campaign=RSS%7CNSNS&amp;utm_source=NSNS&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_content=home</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T19:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <summary>An historical astronomy investigation re-identifies Barnard’s 1892 “vanished” bright star near Venus, but it has little direct relevance to origins-of-life or astrobiology beyond the Venus context.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    In 1892, astronomer Edward Emerson Barnard thought he saw a bright star near Venus, but then it vanished. We may now know why
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/asna.19061720105&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.1002/asna.19061720105&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3724/SP.J.1440-2807.2025.03.05&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.3724/SP.J.1440-2807.2025.03.05&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/asna.19061720105&#34;&gt;[Full Paper] https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/asna.19061720105&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/2509810-star-that-seemed-to-vanish-more-than-130-years-ago-is-found-again/?utm_campaign=RSS%7CNSNS&amp;amp;utm_source=NSNS&amp;amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;amp;utm_content=home&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Astrobiology ➤ University Of Canterbury Team Led Study Of Interstellar Comet 3I/ATLAS</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/university-of-canterbury-team-led-study-of-interstellar-comet-3i-atlas.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/university-of-canterbury-team-led-study-of-interstellar-comet-3i-atlas.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T19:35:04+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Observations and modeling of the interstellar comet 3I/ATLAS provide astrobiology-relevant context on the volatile/organic inventory of extrasolar small bodies, with indirect implications for prebiotic delivery to young planetary systems.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    The comet 3I/ATLAS, discovered by an international team in July this year, is only the third interstellar object ever found in the history of astronomy. It is the first that is bright enough to be seen through amateur telescopes and is currently visible in the Northern Hemisphere. It will make its closest approach to Earth […] The post University Of Canterbury Team Led Study Of Interstellar Comet 3I/ATLAS appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/mnrasl/article/544/1/L31/8247984?login=false&#34;&gt;[Full Paper] https://academic.oup.com/mnrasl/article/544/1/L31/8247984?login=false&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18382&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18382&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26053&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26053&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/university-of-canterbury-team-led-study-of-interstellar-comet-3i-atlas.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ HKUST Launches World’s First Deep-sea Multi-omics Resource Platform Empowering Global Research Into Biological Adaptation In Extreme Environments</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/hkust-launches-worlds-first-deep-sea-multi-omics-resource-platform-empowering-global-research-into-biological-adaptation-in-extreme-environments.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/hkust-launches-worlds-first-deep-sea-multi-omics-resource-platform-empowering-global-research-into-biological-adaptation-in-extreme-environments.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T19:35:05+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Introduces a large deep-ocean multi-omics database resource that can inform astrobiology via comparative biology of extremophile adaptation and habitability analogs, but it is not directly focused on prebiotic chemistry or origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST), in collaboration with the Southern Marine Science and Engineering Guangdong Laboratory (Guangzhou), has launched the world’s first Deep Ocean Omics (DOO) database (https://DeepOceanOmics.org/). As the largest platform of its kind, DOO integrates and analyzes multi-omics data from organisms thriving in the ocean’s most extreme environments, alongside […] The post HKUST Launches World’s First Deep-sea Multi-omics Resource Platform Empowering Global Research Into Biological Adaptation In Extreme Environments appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/nar/advance-article/doi/10.1093/nar/gkaf1096/8307365&#34;&gt;[Full Paper] https://academic.oup.com/nar/advance-article/doi/10.1093/nar/gkaf1096/8307365&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkaf1096/8307365&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkaf1096/8307365&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/hkust-launches-worlds-first-deep-sea-multi-omics-resource-platform-empowering-global-research-into-biological-adaptation-in-extreme-environments.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ Performance Calibration of the Wavefront Sensor’s EMCCD Detector for the Cool Planets Imaging Coronagraph Aboard CSST</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/performance-calibration-of-the-wavefront-sensors-emccd-detector-for-the-cool-planets-imaging-coronagraph-aboard-csst.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/performance-calibration-of-the-wavefront-sensors-emccd-detector-for-the-cool-planets-imaging-coronagraph-aboard-csst.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T18:35:25+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This paper calibrates the EMCCD detector in CSST’s coronagraph wavefront sensor to improve high-contrast exoplanet imaging performance, an enabling technology but not directly focused on origins-of-life or biosignature science.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    The wavefront sensor (WFS), equipped with an electron-multiplying charge-coupled device (EMCCD) detector, is a critical component of the Cool Planets Imaging Coronagraph (CPI-C) on the Chinese Space Station Telescope (CSST). Precise calibration of the WFS’s EMCCD detector is essential to meet the stringent requirements for high-contrast exoplanet imaging. This study comprehensively characterizes key performance parameters […] The post Performance Calibration of the Wavefront Sensor’s EMCCD Detector for the Cool Planets Imaging Coronagraph Aboard CSST appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20386&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20386&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/jimaging11060203&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.3390/jimaging11060203&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.2&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.20386&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.20386&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/performance-calibration-of-the-wavefront-sensors-emccd-detector-for-the-cool-planets-imaging-coronagraph-aboard-csst.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ Understanding Protein Form And Function Better At TU Graz</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/understanding-protein-form-and-function-better-at-tu-graz.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/understanding-protein-form-and-function-better-at-tu-graz.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T18:35:26+00:00</updated>
    <summary>A structural biology study (Cell Press Structure) improving our understanding of protein 3D form–function relationships, broadly relevant to biology but only indirectly connected to origins-of-life questions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Proteins are among the most important building blocks of nature and play a central role in biological processes in all organisms. Accordingly, scientists are keen to understand them as precisely as possible. As polymers of different amino acids, proteins can have different 3-dimensional structures and various functions. However, it is often difficult to determine which […] The post Understanding Protein Form And Function Better At TU Graz appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/structure/fulltext/S0969-2126(25)00263-1?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS0969212625002631%3Fshowall%3Dtrue&#34;&gt;[ScienceDirect] https://www.cell.com/structure/fulltext/S0969-2126(25)00263-1?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS0969212625002631%3Fshowall%3Dtrue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/understanding-protein-form-and-function-better-at-tu-graz.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ Fungi From Chernobyl: Mycobiota Of The Inner Regions Of The Containment Structures Of The Damaged Nuclear Reactor</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/fungi-from-chernobyl-mycobiota-of-the-inner-regions-of-the-containment-structures-of-the-damaged-nuclear-reactor.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/fungi-from-chernobyl-mycobiota-of-the-inner-regions-of-the-containment-structures-of-the-damaged-nuclear-reactor.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T18:35:27+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Survey of diverse fungi colonizing the high-radiation interior of Chernobyl’s reactor shelter, relevant to astrobiology via microbial survival in extreme environments but not directly to origins-of-life mechanisms.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Extensive fungal growth has been detected on the walls and other building constructions in the inner parts of the Shelter of the damaged fourth Unit of the Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant in 1997-98. The mycobiota comprised 37 species of 19 genera. Zygomycetes and ascomycetes were represented by one species each: Mucor plumbeus and Chaetomium globosum, […] The post Fungi From Chernobyl: Mycobiota Of The Inner Regions Of The Containment Structures Of The Damaged Nuclear Reactor appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0953756208615026&#34;&gt;[ScienceDirect] https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0953756208615026&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/fungi-from-chernobyl-mycobiota-of-the-inner-regions-of-the-containment-structures-of-the-damaged-nuclear-reactor.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ Observational Evidence For A Possible Link Between PAH Emission And Dust Trap Locations In Protoplanetary Disks</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/observational-evidence-for-a-possible-link-between-pah-emission-and-dust-trap-locations-in-protoplanetary-disks.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/observational-evidence-for-a-possible-link-between-pah-emission-and-dust-trap-locations-in-protoplanetary-disks.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T18:35:28+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Compares PAH emission strengths across protoplanetary disks with ALMA dust-continuum dust-trap locations, suggesting organic molecules may be sequestered or processed in dust traps—an astrochemistry result with indirect relevance to prebiotic inventories.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAHs) are commonly detected in protoplanetary disks, but it is unclear what causes the wide range of intensities across the samples. In this work, the measured PAH intensities of a range of disks are compared with ALMA dust continuum images, in order to test whether there is evidence that PAHs are frozen […] The post Observational Evidence For A Possible Link Between PAH Emission And Dust Trap Locations In Protoplanetary Disks appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06935&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06935&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.06935&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.06935&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/observational-evidence-for-a-possible-link-between-pah-emission-and-dust-trap-locations-in-protoplanetary-disks.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟤 Radio-Canada ➤ L’ARC tente de recouvrer 10 G $ de prestations liées à la COVID-19</title>
    <link href="https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2216796/prestations-covid-19-revenu-canada-dette"/>
    <id>https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2216796/prestations-covid-19-revenu-canada-dette</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T16:01:40+00:00</updated>
    <summary>This article concerns the Canada Revenue Agency attempting to recover COVID-19 benefit overpayments and has no relevance to origins of life or astrobiology.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Ces montants ont été versés à des bénéficiaires non admissibles, affirme l&amp;#x27;ARC.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/2216796/prestations-covid-19-revenu-canada-dette&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🔴 Astrobiology ➤ Considerations On The Process Of Target Selection For The Comet Interceptor Mission</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/considerations-on-the-process-of-target-selection-for-the-comet-interceptor-mission.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/considerations-on-the-process-of-target-selection-for-the-comet-interceptor-mission.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T18:35:29+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Describes how ESA’s Comet Interceptor will select an as-yet-unknown long-period comet target, offering broad astrobiology context (comet science relevant to volatile/organic delivery) but little direct origins-of-life or prebiotic chemistry content in the abstract.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    Comet Interceptor is an ESA science mission with payload contributions from ESA Member States and with an international participation by JAXA. It is the first mission that is being designed, built, and potentially launched before its target is known. This approach will enable the spacecraft to perform the first mission to a Long Period Comet […] The post Considerations On The Process Of Target Selection For The Comet Interceptor Mission appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper / DOIs Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20521&#34;&gt;[ArXiv Preprint] https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20521&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.20521&#34;&gt;[DOI Link] https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2511.20521&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/considerations-on-the-process-of-target-selection-for-the-comet-interceptor-mission.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>🟠 Astrobiology ➤ Curiosity Mars Rover Views A Rock Made Of Sulfur At Snow Lake</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/curiosity-mars-rover-views-a-rock-made-of-sulfur-at-snow-lake.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/curiosity-mars-rover-views-a-rock-made-of-sulfur-at-snow-lake.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-30T18:35:30+00:00</updated>
    <summary>Curiosity’s imaging and crushing of sulfur-bearing rocks at “Snow Lake” provides Mars geochemical context potentially relevant to past habitability, but it is not a direct origins-of-life study and lacks primary academic sourcing.</summary>
    <content type="html">
    &lt;hr/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    NASA’s Curiosity captured this close-up image of a rock nicknamed “Snow Lake” on June 8, 2024, the 4,209th Martian day, or sol, of the mission. Nine days earlier, the rover had crushed a similar-looking rock and revealed crystalline textures — and elemental sulfur — inside. Astrobiology, Astrogeology, The post Curiosity Mars Rover Views A Rock Made Of Sulfur At Snow Lake appeared first on Astrobiology .
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No direct link found.
    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/curiosity-mars-rover-views-a-rock-made-of-sulfur-at-snow-lake.html&#34;&gt;Read Full Article&lt;/a&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>